Good morning. Uh, a few announcements
before we uh start class. Um, first of
all, I would like to make a series of
apologies. Um, there are a lot of people
watching online. So, I thank everyone
for taking the time to watch uh these
videos online and some of you have been
complaining about the sound quality as
well as the video quality. Uh, first of
all, I want to thank Carol and her team
for making all this possible. But I need
to remind people that this is an
academic facility. This is not set up
for a YouTube live stream. So I
apologize um if this is not up to par.
Um but Yale the Yale Beijing Center was
not set up to be a YouTube live stream
facility. It was set up to an academic
exchange facility. Okay, that's point
one. Um point two is um I made many
factual mistakes yesterday. I've been
making a lot of factor mistakes
throughout uh this course. So, um to be
honest with you,
this is my actually my first time
reading Divine Comedy
in full. Okay? I've taught Divine Comedy
for the past four years, but it's always
I skip through sections that I think are
important so that I can teach it. Uh
because my strategy is to teach to
learn. So I basically learn what I need
in order to teach and that's been very
unfair to uh Dante. Um so if I'm making
mistakes it's because a lot of this
material is new to me and so I see
teaching as a process of co-creation of
co-discovery. Okay. So uh thank you for
your patience and for your uh
understanding.
And again, the what we're trying to do
is we're trying to understand Dante
thematically rather than factually. I
hope that after class you do go and
review what we've learned and make sure
that you understand what's going on and
also to fix a lot of errors. Um and my
third um apology is that I got emotional
yesterday and um I think a lot of it is
that um when I teach I have a lot of
goals in mind. I have a plan in mind and
I get very impatient when um I lose
focus. I like f I like feedback. I like
to be challenged but sometimes when I am
challenged too much I get a bit exa u I
get frustrated. Okay. So I apologize for
for that. Okay. So um before we be in
class I want to I want to address an
issue from last class. No actually first
before I begin are there any questions
from last class that you have?
Okay. All right. Right. So I want to
address an issue from last class which
is the idea of lust. Okay. Um and we
never really reach a satisfactory
resolution to the problem the sin of
lust. Why would lust be an issue? And
again um we have to assume that Donnie
knows what he's doing. So unless we are
able to explain it to ourselves clearly
and explain to others clearly we have
not arrived to the solution. Okay. So um
um Edward when we were talking about
lust yesterday okay you had a very
interesting comment. Could you repeat
that comment? Do do you remember your
comment about Bicarda and uh Francesca
the parallels? You may not remember but
Oh you I'm sorry. I'm I'm I'm sorry.
Jay. Okay. Could could you could you
repeat that?
>> Um, so there seems to be symmetry. Um,
yes. With regards to the looping. I I
don't know. It's like the ex-programmer
in me is thinking like like with Picard,
she she's stuck in the loop right in in
the lower levels of heaven. And then um
where in hell we see that people in lust
in the in that hurricane tornado as well
as uh um uh the people that are uh uh uh
gluttonous, they're they're stuck also
stuck in an endless cycle, right? So I I
just appreciated that symmetry.
>> Yes. Okay. So the key to understanding
um the idea of lust is to appreciate the
symmetry in the um divine comedy. Um you
also need to appreciate the totality of
the divine comedy in that he's
presenting a complete vision. Okay. So
we know from paradise, we know from
paradise that
Dante's ultimate message is to live a
life of faith,
hope, and love.
He goes on to define these three
concepts as faith is the imagination
to believe that God does exist, that
heaven and hell exist, and that God
loves us. Okay, without these things,
it's hard to understand the world and
arrive at truth. Uh, hope is the idea of
arrogance where you have to believe that
you do matter and whatever you do
impacts the universe. That's why people
like Rachel, ROF, Beatatrice, Rebecca
are next to God because these are in
individuals who had no power, who had no
status, but they chose to live a life of
goodness and as a result, God rewards
them the most. Okay. Um, love
is action, right? to not just be passive
but to be active to believe that
injustice anywhere is injustice
everywhere. Okay. And so in other words
what Donnie is really saying is to live
a life of love and imagination. That is
the ultimate message of the divine
comedy. But now we have to reconcile
this message with the theology of the
Catholic Church at this time and how
people understand the world at this
time. Now um in this time there are the
seven deadly sins.
And
now what's interesting is that Dante
does put four the seven deadly sins in
Inferno, right? They are lust,
um, gluttony,
greed,
and wrath.
Okay, so these these four he does put in
the infernal, but there are three others
that he does not actually put in the
infernal. He will put them in purgatory,
but not infernal. Okay? And they are
um envy,
pride,
and sloth. Okay? basically laziness.
All right. Okay. So,
we need so what D does is he replaces
these things with other things. Okay. Um
basically envy, pride, and sloth are not
in inferno. You're not punished for
these things, but you're punished for um
fraud,
violence,
and treachery.
Okay, not only that, but he separates he
separates the inferno uh with geographic
uh dividers. Okay, remember how he they
they they cross the Aaron River in order
to access um the inferno, but then they
also have to cross the river sticks to
access this, which is the capital city
of Inferno. Okay. And but even when we
go inside this, we'll find that there
actually also major geographic dividers
as well. So what Donna is is suggesting
is that the more you climb into hell,
the greater the crime. Okay. So we need
to we need to to think about what the
difference is um amongst these different
sins. And I mean the most basic
difference is lust, gluttony, greed and
wrath. There are things you do to
yourself. Okay. And violence, fraud,
treachery is are things you do to other
people. Okay. That that is the clearest
difference. Um and what this matters is
that if you with violence, fraud and
treachery, you are disrupting others
capacity to live a good life. All right?
Uh so that's point one. Um point two is
traditionally these things these seven
de sins are an expression of the ego
right it's like too much you are you
want things too much you are expressing
ego too much and that's why you have
these seven deadly sins but we already
said that in paradise arrogance is key
to hope so How do you reconcile this
dichotomy? Right? And the answer is that
what Dante is going to do is show that
you have these things, lust, gluttony,
greed, and wrath because you don't have
enough ego. Does that make sense? Not
enough will. All right. Not enough will
and desire.
All right.
So if you if you reread divine comedy
and you look at these four uh circles,
lust, gluttony, greed, and wrath, it's
like they don't have enough ego. They
don't have enough will. They don't have
enough hope. Okay. Uh uh do you have a
question, Jor?
>> Uh well, that's that's quite powerful to
me because um you're saying that uh it's
a spectrum like ego, free will,
imagination is a spectrum. Yes.
>> And it goes it goes
on the paradise side positive and it and
and the lack of it causes
positive death
>> right okay yeah exactly okay so let let
me give you an example to illustrate
this with will okay with sorry with lust
so again the story of lust is
franciscoca who f who is married but she
falls in love with um her husband's
brother and they have this illicit
affair the husband finds out and kills
both of them and when for when Francisco
says is that, "Oh, what motivated me is
um I was reading these romance novels
and I was so enraptured
by the plot, by the idea of falling in
love with someone else that I just did
it." Okay. And and if you know your
literature, you know that this is the
plotline of Madame Bovery, right? By by
um um by Yes. Right. That's exactly the
plot line. Okay. This, you know, very
bory woman. and she's bored. She's
bored. She read these romance novels and
that's why she starts an affair. Okay,
so this is this is how he depicts lust.
But normally we depict lust as maybe uh
the most common example is you really
like like a woman and you you know pay
her a lot of money, right, for sex,
prostitution, right? So this is a very
different conception where uh in the
normal understanding prostitution it's
the expression of your ego like see I
have a lot of money I I can buy you out.
Whereas with the Francisca story, it's
not enough will and desire. It's like
you are escaping your life, right?
You're in falling in love with an idea
as opposed to a person. Okay? And now to
further illustrate this further, I'm
going to give you three examples. And
then what I want you guys to do is to
rank them according to sin. Okay? The
first example is
[clears throat]
um you love a woman and you give her I
don't know a million dollars to sleep
with her. Okay, basically a million
dollars. [snorts]
Second is um you fall in love with a
beautiful actress. Okay, who like who
knows I like like just anyone. Okay, I I
don't actually know famous Hollywood
actresses. Jennifer Lopez, maybe. Okay.
All right. So, you write you spend the
rest of your life writing love letters
to Jennifer Lopez. Okay.
I I seriously don't don't know that many
Hollywood actress actresses. And the
last thing you do is okay, we are living
in an age of AI. So, you buy yourself an
AI wife. Okay. A robotic wife.
Right
now, I want you guys to use imagine and
and tell me like of these three, which
one is the worst? In Dant's opinion,
which one is the absolute worst? Yes,
>> I think probably the third one cuz uh
you don't really need to like that much
of that much of like a strong will to
process like a sex robot. And um and and
the second one will be the second like
uh um so will be maybe like uh keep
writing love letters to the Hollywood
actress actress cuz it's just like
you're not really taking the actions,
right? You're just like writing the love
letters and uh at least the simple one
is just to like to hire a prostitute to
pay her a million dollar. At least
you're like,
>> you don't care about $7 million, man.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Sorry.
>> Yeah. All right. Okay. Yeah. Okay. Any
other
interpretations or opinions? Yes.
>> I think the first one of giving the
million dollars is the worst sin. And
then uh the love the love letters is the
second sin and the AI wife is the third
sin.
>> Okay. So, explain your logic. I think
the the million dollars is the worst sin
because you can directly negatively
affect someone else because with the
other two like writing the love letters,
they're just receiving your praise. With
the AI wife, it's more damaging
yourself. Whereas the first one, you're
kind of coercing someone else into doing
something bad. So, it could affect her
future capacity to love or
have a connection.
>> Okay. Anyone else? Yes,
>> I think the if you're fall in love with
a actress I mean no matter what uh he or
she is a celebrity right so it doesn't
mean that celebrity cannot be love but
it because love is free will right so
you can love love her can love anybody
want this is real true love I suppose
but AI wife is different because AI is
not real person so uh I don't think the
love can be uh produced you know if you
just fall in love with something and Uh
and also when you're in love with uh uh
some people give them dollar. I think
it's it's all right. Unless you just you
don't only want sex, you want to have
comfort, maybe it's okay. Just like you
give your money to your wife. Right.
>> Right. Um anyone else? Uh yes.
>> So in Dante's time, these aren't my
opinions. In Dante's time, then they
would see lust as um natural and
unnatural. And natural lust would lead
to marriage and reproduction.
>> Yes. And so, um, if God is love, you
could not have bring God into the number
three, the robots,
um, relationship. So, that would be the
worst. Yes. And there's a possibility
that
>> you fall in love with the prostitute and
get married or Jennifer Lopez falls in
love with you and gets married and has
babies and that's good in God's eyes,
>> right? Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Good.
Number three. Yes. Anyone else?
>> All right. Yes.
>> Um, so it's like the triangle theory of
love. It's either errors which is
passion with the body and then there's
friendship which is connection with the
soul and then commitment or something
which is linked into marriage. And so in
that triangle the prostitute fulfills
the body part. So it's not as bad. It's
one part of one aspect of love and the
letters for Jennifer Lopez is the soul
connection or friendship aspect but I
think the worst is the robot one. Uh
because it's neither all all three.
Yeah.
>> Good. Okay. Wait. The obvious answer is
number three. Okay.
Um and how and how we know is we can
actually go back and and like use these
three criteria faith, hope and love.
Okay. And I mean there are different
formulations you provide. Both of you
provide really good formulations but the
main reason is you basically given up on
yourself right think about that think
about it. You marry a robotic wife. That
is despair.
You don't take yourself seriously
anymore.
Right? You're so lonely. uh you are so
uh humiliated that you're like you know
what I'll just go I'll just go and marry
a robotic wife just keep myself company
okay so for Dante and for the Catholic
church as well number three is the worst
possible
um sin and it's expression yes we say
that uh sins that impact others are
worse so like the robot robotic wife is
only concerning yourself but giving a
million would be aband ending yourself
and also the other's life because
because she has a million then she's
going to go into a life of like spending
and all. So concerns two person which I
see as worse.
>> Right. Right. Right. You're right. Okay.
So it's conditional. Okay. We're
assuming that in number one um she's a
prostitute and she just agrees, right?
Um like like she's willing to do this.
We agree. But if if she if she's been
coerced to do it, then obviously number
one it's a lot worse, right? And we'll
actually go into that um as we descend
into hell. Okay. So, but we're we're
assuming like this is not impacting the
other person. Okay. But thank you for
that. Yes.
>> Can we also say it's three because it
inspires the least imagination.
>> Exactly. Right. Yeah. So again, we have
to think about the totality of the
divine comedy. Right. We want to live a
life of faith, hope, and love. And
living a life of faith, hope, and love
means taking yourself seriously. Okay?
like don't be passive, be active. And
number three, um, is basically giving up
life. Okay? And that's why lust is a
problem because lust is like you're
escaping into a fantasy, right?
Francesca is escaping into a fantasy. If
she really loved um the husband's
brother, they would just elope together,
right? But it's not like that. It's
like, you know, she she what what she's
doing is she's reading a romance novel
and she's trying to project her
fantasies onto another person. Right?
And she doesn't really care who that
person is. She has absolutely no
feelings for that person. And when but
when she does that, she's not taking
herself seriously enough,
right? She doesn't really have uh faith,
hope, and love. Okay? Does that make
sense? So that helps us explain why lust
is a problem and how it fits into the
larger Danten cosmology.
All right? Any questions before I
continue? All right. My next point is
this. Um for the next two three days we
will finish the inferno and the inferno
is very different from paradiso. Okay.
So think of paradiso
as ultimately
sorry this is um it's fine.
Okay thank you vision. Okay or the
apocalypse.
So in
thank you. So so in the in the biblical
tradition in the religious tradition uh
the apopulates means revelation. Okay.
What god shows you what the vision is.
So think of paradiso as uh Dante's last
will and testament. He's telling us what
his vision for the universe is for the
for the future for uh for us is. Okay.
The Inferno is different. The Inferno is
what we call prophecy.
[snorts]
And you're like, "Wait a minute. Aren't
they the same thing?" Okay, today, yes,
they are the same thing. But back then,
prophecy is very different from vision.
Okay, prophecy is a critique of the
present. Right? Right? If you read the
Bible, all these people, Isaiah,
Jeremiah, Ezekiel, they've come down to
criticize the Israelites to crit to like
say you guys are sinning. Okay? If you
don't sin, God's going to come and
punish you. Okay? That's what prophecy
is. Not one of like
like fortunetelling, but one of social
critique. So that that's what the
inferno is. It's fundamentally a social
critique. [snorts]
And so what I want to do today is
basically read the Inferno and
understand it ultimately as Dante
criticizing his society, the people
around him.
And also what I want to do is I want us
to think about do his criticisms of
quarantine society apply to us today.
Okay. But this is important is that
there's [snorts] a really good reason
why
the kadia okay at the time in history
when wrote it's called laabia but later
on people apply the word divine to it
meaning it is the word of god okay
because
dies in the year 1321
and um in year 1321 when he dies
people don't really understand what this
is what's going on, right? Because we
have in paradise uh Peter lombasting the
Catholic Church. We also have Beatrice
in her final words cursing humanity.
Right? You guys are hopeless. We sent
the savior to you and you ignored him
and you're all going to burn in hell.
Okay? And this is very much part of
prophetic tradition, right? So, if
you're reading this in the year 1321,
you
um just don't know what's going on. But
this happen something happens in year
that convinces
that everyone that Dante is a prophet.
Do you know what happens in year 1357
in Italy? Can you guys guess? I'm pretty
sure you know what it is.
Come on.
This thing kills A lot of people the
black death. Okay.
And how would they interpret the black
death?
Divine retribution, divine judgment.
Okay, you understand? What happens after
black death is the renaissance, right?
When they fully embrace Dante. You guys
understand? Send the sequence events.
1321 Donnie dies and he's cursing
cursing humanity. says like the heavens
curse you, right? And then was like,
well, you know, so what? 1357, the black
death, where at least, okay, at least a
third of Europe dies. Can you imagine
that? A third of Europe dies. Some
places it's even
half or threequarters of the population.
Okay, this is a complete
disaster. Okay. The worst possible
calamity to befall on humanity at this
time. And so you can only interpret this
as divine retribution or judgment. Okay.
All right.
And Dante
knows it's coming, right? Because all
prophets knows knows it's coming. That's
why they're so angry, right? They're
like, you know, if you just read the
Bible, whether it's Isaiah or uh Daniel
or just any of the prophets, okay,
they're really, really angry because
they know it's coming. They know God
will have his vengeance, will have his
retribution. Okay, but this again
creates a paradox for us because if
Dante knows it's coming and he's very
angry, but he also says that God is all
loving, all forgiveness, all mercy. How
can we reconcile this paradox? What's
the logic of this?
>> Yes.
>> Uh that uh God is trying to show
humanity something.
>> No, he's not trying to show, right?
Because a third of humanity will die.
What? What's going on here?
This is punishment. We just said that if
you love someone, you don't punish
someone.
Okay, let's use your imagination. Okay,
let's just say we're a parent and we
have a child for for whatever reason.
Okay, we don't know why, but for
whatever reason, this child has become a
drug addict
and he or she commits a lot of crime in
order to feed his or her drug addiction.
If we truly love our child, what would
we do? Yes. U send him to the rehab.
Send him to the rehabitation.
>> Okay. syrup,
>> right?
Uh any other suggestions?
The person has
>> kick him out.
>> Call the police, right? Because he or
she has stolen a lot of money, commit a
lot of crimes in order to feed his or
her drug addiction. He or she belongs in
jail. Okay. Is this retribution? Is this
vengeance? Or is it love? What's the
difference?
>> Love.
>> But why is love? They're trying to
control the amount of harm they have on
other people.
>> Okay. Any other
>> this you're bringing up the the good
Samaritan issue in the Bible where like
the per the person who like uh helps
them is actually enabling them and the
person that like ignores them makes them
realize on their own their errors and
fix themselves.
>> Okay. Right. Okay. So the logic is this.
The logic is like if you truly love
someone, you want what's best for that
person, right? You want that person to
live the best possible life. That that's
what love is. And if the person is like
has a drug addiction, that person cannot
live his or her best life. She had to do
something about it. Okay? And like
enabling it, sending sending him or her
to rehab, that doesn't really solve the
problem. Okay? Okay, what you have to do
is basically let him or her hit rock
bottom before he or she can lift himself
up. Okay, does that make sense? Okay, so
apply this to the black death.
Why would God unleash a black death? God
didn't do this, but I'm saying like why
would people think it's it's it's God?
>> Humanity is humanity has a lot of
problems and God needs to make us reach
rock bottom to realize our problems and
fix them ourselves.
>> Right? Okay. So that is the message of
the divine comedy. Okay. And it's the
inverse of Catholic Church. The Catholic
Church is
don't screw up and you go to heaven. Um
and if you screw up, you go to hell.
Okay. So it's a high risk situation.
For Dante, there is no risk. God will
forgive you always. But because God will
always forgive you always, that gives
you responsibility
to live your best life. Okay? to live a
life of faith, hope and love. And if you
cannot live that, even if you want to
live that, you cannot live that, then
God
will intervene in a way that permits you
to live that. Okay. So another saying
this is society has has become so
corrupt has become so evil so sinful
that an ordinary person like Dante
cannot live a life of faith hope and
love anymore in that situation there
will be divine judgment. Okay, there the
God has to intervene because if God
truly loves us, God needs to ensure
that we have the opportunity to live a
life of hope, faith and love. All right.
Yes.
Uh I agree with your professor and and
also it make me recall memory that you
know if the uh your uh for example
family member was just being you know in
the sick bat right and keep waiting for
death and at that time you know I think
a lot of people just don't believe in
money they believe in God because only
the god can can you know can give him
back or can just you know let him
recover. So maybe God is trying to test
people and just let them to know that uh
what you chasing for the money the power
is useless in front of the units right
just like you know the uh so
[clears throat] right now uh you know uh
we can call COVID 19 right so maybe yeah
>> okay all right okay so so um to start
off our discussion of Dante as a prophet
okay as a social critic uh as someone
who is telling people that divine
vengeance is coming um this is a comment
from uh YouTube. It's the same person
who who commented about uh Peter and the
coin. Okay. It's a very good comment. So
So we're going to read it to to like
understand
uh Don as a prophet. Okay. Uh uh Carol,
could you read please?
>> Sure.
>> It is wild how many people in this
lecture treat Dante like a harmless
academic monument, completely missing
why he was a true hero for the people.
Dante Aliggaryi was not born into
absolute luxury or elite upper class. As
a son of a low-level money lender, he
had to completely hustle his way through
his academics using sheer intellectual
genius to break into elite philosophical
and geometric circles. He was also
hardened a hardened combat veteran who
fought on the front lines as a cavalry
man for the Florentine army at the
bloody battle of Campalino in 1289. He
was a champion who used his hard-earned
political power to protect ordinary
citizens from a corrupt predatory
establishment. In 1300, he was elected
as a ruling minister of Florence and
immediately passed bold laws to strip
the corrupt local Franciscan Inquisitor
of his power, stopping the church from
weaponizing heresy checklist to extort
bribes and plunder the financial purses
of wealthy families. Dante even
sacrificed his own personal life for the
law, voting to exile his own best friend
to keep the peace and prove that justice
belongs to the people, not political
factions. The papal establishment struck
back with absolute malice. Pope Bonafas
Bonafas VII lured Dante to Rome on a
fake diplomatic mission while secretly
launching a military coup that tore down
Dante's home, seized all his assets, and
locked his name into the infamous book
of the nail registry, sentencing him to
be burned alive at the stake. Forced
into a brutal 19-year exile as a hunted
fugitive, Dante never backed down. He
proved that the ultimate weapon against
a blood soaked political apparatus is
radical uncensored love and spiritual
freedom. He used his poetry to expose
the rulers who financialized grace,
putting corrupt popes in hell while they
were still alive while preaching that
the entire universe is actually powered
by his decentralized unbanable divine
love that no empire can ever trap behind
a payw wall. The institution was so
terrified of his message of human
liberation that in 1329, Cardinal Bert
de BJ sent armed men to dig up his dead
body and burn his bones to ashes,
forcing local Franciscan monks to hide
his skeleton in a wall for centuries.
Dante was a rogue insider who gave up
his wealth, his status, and his safety
to shield the divine spark and build an
eternal escape hatch for humanity.
>> Okay. Um so of course there's a bit of
exaggeration in it. Okay. But the
essence is very much true. He is he was
a prophet and this is a life of a
prophet. One of constant alienation,
persecution and exile. All right? And
there's no other way. Um he chose to
live a life of faith, hope and love. And
when he cannot do that then he knows
that society is unjust. When society is
unjust then God will eventually have to
intervene. Okay. And that's why in Pyiso
in this place of uh grace and mercy and
love Peter and Beatrice will go on this
tirade against humanity. Okay? It is a
promise of divine judgment. All right?
And so we will what what what we'll do
today and tomorrow and we will focus on
what's going on in Florence Florente
society to make Dante
uh demand divine vengeance retribution.
Okay. Not not only is he a prophet
telling people that divine retribution
is coming, but he's also a messenger of
God, an angel who is demanding from God
de divine retribution and judgment.
Okay. All right. So, uh we're going to
pick up from inferno. Uh where where did
we end last time? Okay. So, so so so
let's let's do number 10. Okay.
All right.
But are there any questions about this
before we start reading? Again, the goal
for today and tomorrow is figure out
what's going on in Florentine society to
make Dante so angry at the world. Okay.
Why does he feel so hopeless?
All right. Okay. All right. So, let's
let's uh
>> Okay. Cantoen.
Now by a narrow path that ran between
those torments and the ramparts of the
city, my master moves ahead. I
following. Oh highest virtue, you who
lead me through these circles of
transgression at your will. Do speak to
me and satisfy my longings. Can those
who lie within the sepokers be seen? The
lids in fact have all been lifted. No
guardians washing over them. and he to
me they'll all be shuttered up when they
return here from Jehoshaphat together
with the flesh they left above within
this region is the cemetery of Epicurus
and his followers all those who say the
soul dies with body and so the question
you have asked of me will soon find
satisfaction while we're here as will
the longing you have hid from me
>> okay all right so so remember where we
are okay we've crossed the river sticks
and we are now in the city city of disc
which is the capital of hell and so we
are now meeting the worst offenders
These are people who have not who've not
only sinned them sin against themselves
but they've sinned against others
especially God. And uh the first people
we meet are the heretics. Okay. The
people who have misled
uh people from God and their punishment
is they basically lie uh in these tombs
and they're burning to to death. And
Virgil says the main heresy is the the
Epiricus and his fathers. Eper the
Epericans
believe that there is no soul. There's
no heaven and hell. So all that means is
while you're on earth, just have a
blast, man. Have a feast. Eat the best
food. Have sex every day. Uh wear the
best clothes. Just enjoy yourself. And
for Dante, this is just pure heresy.
Okay, he hates his idea because if you
think about it, why he hates his idea is
that it completely removes the need for
faith, hope, and love, right? If there's
nothing after this, why have faith? Why
have hope? Why have love? Okay. So, for
Dante, he takes great offense at the
Epicurans and everyone that's burning
here are the Epicurans. Okay. All right.
Let's keep on going.
Line 19.
And I, good God, the only reason I have
hit my heart was that I might speak
briefly, and you long since encouraged
me in this. Oh, Tuscan, you who pass a
life across the fiery city with such
seemly words. Be kind enough to stay
your journey here. Your accent makes it
clear that you belong among the natives
of the noble city I may have dealt with
so vindictively.
>> Okay, so Dante and Virgil are talking
and then someone overhears them. This is
Kavakante who is uh someone that uh
Donnie uh knew very well. Okay.
Kavakante. And Kavakante hears Donnie's
accent says, "Hey, you must from you
must be from Florence. Let's talk."
Okay. All right. Keep on going.
>> Line 28.
This sound had burst so unexpectedly out
of once a pulker that trembling, I then
drew a little closer to my guide. But he
told me, "Turn around. What are you
doing? That's for Anata who has risen
there. You'll see all of him from the
waist up. My eyes already were intent on
his. And up he rose his forehead and his
chest as if he had tremendous scorn for
hell. My guide his hands encouraging and
quick thrust me between the pokers
toward him, saying, "Your words must be
appropriate." When I draw closer to
closer to his poker, he glanced at me
and as of disdain, he asked of me, "Who
were your ancestors?"
because I wanted so to be compliant, I
had no thing for him from him. I told
them all at this he lifted up his brows
a bit, then said, "They were ferocious
enemies of mine and of my parents and my
party, so that I had to scatter them
twice over." If they were driven out, I
answered him, they still returned both
times from every quarter. But yours were
never quick to learn that art. At this
there rose another shade alongside,
uncovered to my sight down to his chin.
I think that he had risen on his knees.
He looked around me just as he longed to
see if I had come with someone else. But
then his expectations bent, he said in
tears. "If it is your high intellect
that lets you journey here through this
blind prison, where is my son? Why is he
not with you?"
>> Okay, so this is very important. Okay,
so let me explain what's going on. Um
Dante is talking to someone and then
someone else overhears and this person
is Kavakante. Sorry. Sorry, I I I
misspoke. Okay, the first shade is not
Kavante. The second shade is Kamak Kante
and Kamakante knows it's Dante and Kamak
says um if it is your high intellect
that let you journey here where is my
son okay what what is important is that
um the son of the shade his name is
Gaido and Gaido and Dante are
competitors they're both poets they're
trying to be the best poet in Florence
right And what go and what cover is
saying to Dante is hey if you are able
to make it here with your poetry then
where's my son right he's at least equal
to you
it doesn't make sense all right so so
let's see what Dante uh says
line 61 I answered my own powers have
not brought me he who awaits me there
leads me through here perhaps to one
your guido did disdain his words, the
nature of his punishment. These had
already let me read his name. Therefore,
my answer was so fully made. Then
suddenly erect, he cried, "What's that?"
He did disdain. He's not still alive.
The sweet light does not strike against
his eyes. And when he noticed how I
hesitated a moment in my answer, he fell
back supine and did not show himself
again.
>> Okay, so this is a really crucial scene.
Okay, so imagine what's going on.
Kelante asks Dante, "Where is my son?"
And Dante is like, "Um, uh, God disdains
him." And then Kavakan is like, "Then my
son is dead." And D and D knows for a
fact that his son is not dead. Okay. But
D does not correct him. All right. Do do
you guys understand what's going on?
Here's the question.
Why is Dante doing this?
Okay, let's imagine if it were you,
right? Like you meet the father of your
of your friend
and your father says, "Why isn't your
friend?"
And the father says, "Why why isn't my
son with you?" What should your answer
be?
>> Maybe just tell him the truth. If I were
a friend of
>> Yeah, just tell him like he's living a
great life back in Florence. that's why
he couldn't be here, right? But instead,
Dante kind of lies and says, "Well,
um, it's your son is kind of dead." Why
would he do that?
Uh, yes.
I mean, so that the father knows that
the son is not in hell because if he was
dead, well, I mean, because he is in
hell. So, um, if his son were dead, then
he would know if he would be in hell.
So,
>> that's a generous explanation, but, um,
it's you're still lying. You know, he's
alive back in Florence, right? Why would
he do that? Yes.
>> Oh, he's in hell. Go with the flow.
Right. Like, I noticed too like as he as
we descend, you know, further we
descend, he his his responses seem to be
more pious, more cruel.
>> Okay. All right. So, let me tell you a
story. Okay, this happened um in China
where there were two students at
uh Chinua University or was it Piggy
University? I can't I can't remember.
Okay, but one of the top university in
China and they're best friends and
they're they're roommates and one the
one of the girls receives a graduate off
from Princeton University. Okay.
and she but she she's not in she's not
in a dorm. It's her classmate who gets
it. Okay. So, what does the classmate
do? They're best friends. They're both
they've been dormates for the past four
years. They're both aspiring to go to
Davy League. One of them gets in, the
envelope comes to the other person. What
this other person do with that envelope?
Can you guys guess?
>> She throws it away.
>> Isn't there like email now? I I I
understand. Thank you. I'm saying like
before in the '9s. Okay.
>> Why would that happen?
>> Jealousy.
>> Yeah. Can you But but like but like but
like let's explain this. Okay. Let's
film this. They've been living together
for four years, right? They are the best
university in the world. Regardless of
what happens, both will aspire to both
will live great lives, right? Even if
even if they say in China, they're still
going to be great people. They'll be
rich and all that. Yes.
>> I think it's the fact that it's uh
harder to accept the person you are the
closest with who are equal to you in
every way, at least in your eyes,
suddenly got so elevated out of you. So
that's there's also a luri that if a
crab is trying to climb out of the boat,
the other crabs will grab him down.
>> No. Okay, I understand that. Okay,
that's that that that that's correct.
Yes, I understand. But I'm I'm saying
like what sort of culture, what sort of
environment would would create that,
right? Because in theory,
right? You would want the best for your
friend.
>> You you like like if if you received the
envelope, you would open it and you' be
like, "Oh my god, my my best friend got
into Princeton. Let me tell the whole
world. Let's let's organize a big
surprise party for her." Right? That's
what you should naturally do. So, so the
question I'm asking is like what sort of
culture,
what sort of environment, what sort of
society would make someone do that? Yes.
>> A culture that
>> Oh, sorry. Sorry. You you Okay.
>> That could be meritocracy because if you
think you provided the same efforts then
if someone has something you
>> It's a meritocracy. Okay. It's a
meritocracy. This this is the key.
Yes. Okay. And how do we know it's a
meritocracy? Because we live in it.
Okay. We know exactly what happens in a
meritocracy.
All these students. But did did you
>> just to add I think I that was what I
was trying to say also. You see this a
lot in sibling rivalry.
>> Yes.
>> Too. Because the closer you are to
another person, the more more it impacts
you, their success, their so you know.
>> Right. So a meritocracy is a high
pressure
winner takes all unforgiving culture,
right?
Dante and Gido are competing to be the
best poet in Italy. And right now who
who's probably in the lead?
>> No, the other guy. Okay. Right. You
understand?
>> Yeah.
>> That's why he tears up that envelope.
He's like, screw this. Do you
understand?
Okay. So, there's a lot of things going
on and that's why this is a great story
because it shows you how sinful Dante
is, right? He's full of fear, anger, and
hatred. But at the same time, it gives
you glimpse into the larger Florentine
society where only the best are
appreciated. Everyone else is discarded.
Right? And it's no different from today
because we because back then it was a
bit of a meritocracy but today it's also
a meritocracy. And do you guys live like
living in a meritocracy?
Probably not. Okay. I I mean if you I
don't but what but I mean you could.
Okay. But so do do you guys understand
this?
>> Hey what's going on? Yes.
>> It's a culture of winners and losers,
right? Never in a pure meritocracy it
will be a hierarchical and obviously by
numbers sheer number of souls being
happy you'd have less of them. Right.
>> Right. Okay. And ideally you would live
in a society of community right where
people are helping each other. But here
in Florence at this time it's winner
take all. It's um it's Yes.
But meritocracy
um gives equal chances to relatively can
give equal chances to people who were
not born who didn't win the birth
lottery and also you could say it has
high efficiency.
>> Yes. Yes. That that that's what you what
you were taught. What's Yeah. But yes,
[clears throat]
>> I see some quite interesting parallels
between uh the meritocracy argument and
how we saw in Paradiso the arguments
against logic because it's this idea
that oh we have this system and through
logic or pure meritocracy we will come
to some ideal solution but we see both
with meritocracy and the idea of logic
that we don't. There's something deeper
there.
>> Yeah. I mean like okay I mean like let's
think about how schools work nowadays
right
kids go in and they compete against each
other on tests and if you do well on
tests you're smart if you do on well if
you don't do well on test you're stupid
and the smart kids are funneled into
elite universities where they compete
against more people then they are
funneled into life where they compete
against more people right are these kids
happy
probably Not okay. So then you ask
yourself what's the point of this? Yes.
>> So what would be the opposite of
meritocracy? You know what would be what
would what other system would you put in
place rather than meritocracy?
>> Okay.
Um well what are some other options we
have?
Because um to me intuitively the
opposite of meritocracy is like nepotism
or favoritism or uh you know like
you know birthright and that stuff.
>> Okay. So so so yeah you're right. Okay.
So one possibility is the aristocracy,
right? Where you have nobility in charge
and they're in charge forever. Why would
that be a bad system?
Yes,
>> because power is inherited. So you have
to win the birth lottery in aristocracy.
Some nobility is passed down through
blood and you cannot other people cannot
have a chance.
>> Hey, so there's no social mobility. Yes.
>> Yeah. I mean if the same people are in
power then and then the parents always
like give their same values to their
children then nothing would ever change.
So there will be no like mobility,
social mobility, no like change
basically. So
>> So are you saying we have social
mobility in a meritocracy
>> more than in more than an
>> I would say more than in an aristocracy.
>> Okay. Um
I suggest going to an elite university
and like just doing a study of like how
many rich kids there are there. Okay. As
opposed to like poor kids. Yes.
Yeah. Isn't Isn't half of all elite
universities like legacy?
>> Yes. I I appreciate that. Yes. I I Yes.
>> And are you calling that a meritocracy
then? It seems like
>> that's a problem, right? Like Yes.
>> Yeah. I was just going to say
meritocracy. That's why it's just a
label, right? It's whatever we want to
call it. It's just using the same stick
to measure society like money [snorts]
like all these prestige and all that,
right? Um
>> okay. So, so, so, so, okay, we have a
situation where, um, basically half the
kids at these elite universities, um,
but but not at Yale, right? [laughter]
No, not at Yale. Um, so at least half
the kids there are legacies. Um, so it's
basically an aristocracy or an
oligarchy. Okay. How But how are they
different from previous nobility?
Yes.
>> I feel like in a meritocracy,
people value their own personal skill
more than where they come from and like
the connections that they have. For for
example, in a meritocracy, we value
education. We value people who have
skill and talent and we value like
critical thinking and problem solving
and all these skills rather than
like who your family is and what your
birthright is.
>> Is that really true? Yes.
>> So I think mar meritocracy is like a
upgrade from aristocracy which is purely
legacy. So like right now in America
elite university if you read Columbia
professors um the excellent sheep it
talks about the problem of marriiocracy
that kids in elite universities think
that they earn their place by hard work.
But I also learned about educational
philosophy and research. We know that uh
social economic status have a better
bigger impact on the the kids IQ than
the IQ itself like you know on the kids
uh academic performance than their brain
powers and everything else combined. Um
and so therefore metocracy today it is
still in a way affected by aristocracy.
But if you truly believe in meritocracy,
you'll be like, "Oh, I earned all this
because I worked so hard and you didn't
know that your parents actually also
gave you the birth lottery."
>> Yeah. So that's the first problem with
meritocracy. Okay. Yes, I know
meritocracy is about fairness, but why
is it then that we live in in a point in
history when there's never been much
much more inequality and lack of social
mobility. Okay, this is just
economically true. There's just like
this time in history, the year we're
living in now is the most unequal in
human history. Okay? And a lot of the
reason is that uh people who been from
meritocracy think they deserved it.
Right? So they are much more likely to
increase inequality because they think
that this is fair whereas before
nobility at least they were embarrassed
about it. Right? Okay. That's the first
problem. Second problem is I don't think
it's actually true that in meritocracy
people care about skills and talent. I
think in meritocracy people people care
more about credentials,
right?
And
sometimes credentials and skills are not
the same thing.
Okay. So, so, so, so again, we're we're
just thinking about our context and how
to apply it to Donny's context. Okay.
But regardless, one major issue at this
time in history in Florence is the
competition among people. So that they
feel they think that they're all
enemies. Even friends think they're
enemies. Okay? And this anidote
illustrates that,
right? And I mean this I mean like what
Donnie did is it is it pretty bad?
Cool. It's cruel, right? I mean, it's no
different from the classmate ripping up
that Princeton offer, right? And just
like hiding it from her classmate. It's
pretty cruel. And that's the idea here
where this competition is leading people
to the greatest cruelty, unimaginable cu
cruelty. Like the father is dead, man.
The father is burning in hell and you
still have to punish him. Excuse me.
>> It's like killing him twice.
>> Yeah. God, right? Because like your only
consolation if you're burning in hell is
well my at least my son is doing well
back in Florence. He's still a great
poet, right? That be because like like
obviously him asking the question just
just shows him how proud he is of his
son, right? If you Donna can get here
well so can my son, right? So it's his
love for the son and that pisses down
like no your son your son is also
burning in hell. Thank you very much.
Okay.
All right.
But but you see how this one story is
just revealing to us a larger social
context. Okay. All right. Uh let's let's
keep on going.
>> Line 73.
But that greathearted one, the other
shade at whose request I'd stayed, did
not change aspect or turn aside his head
or lean or bend, and taking up his words
where he'd le left off. If they were
slow, he said, to learn that art that is
more torment to me than his than this
bed. And yet the lady whose ruler here
will not have her face kindled 50 times
before you learn how heavy is that art.
And so may you return to the sweet
world. Tell me, why are those citizens
so cruel against my kin and on all of
their decrees?
>> Okay, so now Donniey's left Kavakante
because Kavakant is in despair, right?
Uh, and now he's talking to Finita. Uh,
and Finita is also contemporary of
Dante. And Ferinita um is an aristocrat
who led um Donny's enemies to conquer
Florence. Remember at this time at this
time, Florence is in a civil war between
the Gib Giblines who are aristocrats,
nobility, and the GS. The gues are
merchants. They are the middle class.
Okay? And Donnie belongs to the Gs.
Okay? So this is a class warfare. And um
the Giblines uh are supported by the
Holy Roman Emperor and the Gelves are
supported by the Pope. Eventually the GS
themselves will fracture between the
black welves and the white Gelves. Okay.
Uh but um the Farah uh uh Farah Nita he
is a Gibling. Okay. He's an aristocrat.
Okay. All right. Um, can you keep on
reading
[snorts]
>> line 85? To which I said, the carnage,
the great bloodshed that stained the
waters of the aria of red have led us to
such prayers in our temple. He sighed
and shook his head, then said, "In that,
I did not act alone, but certainly I'd
not have joined the others without
cause, but where I was alone was there
where all the was all the rest would
have annihilated Florence had I not
interceded forcefully." Okay, so this is
a very famous episode from this history
where after the Giblines uh take over
Florence, they want to kill all the Gs.
Okay, they want to kill all the families
of the gues and um destroy all the
property of the GS. And Feronita, he
intervenes and says no, we can't do that
because this is Florence. We are first
and foremost citizens of Florence and
then we are giblings, then we are
partisans. Okay. So, so he heroically
saves Florence and uh Donnie is paying
him homage here. Keep on going.
>> Line 94. Ah, as I hope your seed may yet
find peace, I asked, so may you help me
to undo the knot that here has snarled
my course of thought. It seems, if I
hear right, that you can see beforehand
that which time is carrying, but you're
denied the sight of present things. We
see even as a as men who are far-sighted
those things he said that are that are
remote from us. The highest lord allotss
us that much light. But when events draw
near or are our minds are useless. Were
we not informed by others we should know
nothing of your human state. So you can
understand how our awareness will die
completely at the moment when the portal
of the future has been shut. Then, as if
penitent for my omission, I said, "Will
you now tell that fallen man his son is
still among the living ones, and if a
while ago I held my tongue before his
question, let him know it was because I
had in mind the doubt you've answered."
>> Okay, so here Dante is so embarrassed,
he tells Fer Feronita, I can't go back
to Kavakante and apologize, right? But
could you do it for me, please? Okay,
he's [laughter] all right. So again, it
shows you how problematic Dante is at st
at at this stage in his life, right?
He's full of fear, hatred, and uh envy.
Uh keep on going.
Line 115. And now my master was
recalling me, so that more hurriedly I
asked the spirit to name the others who
were there with him. He said, "More than
the thousand lie with me, the second
Frederick, is but one among them, as is
the cardinal. I name no others." With
that he hid himself and pondering the
speech that seemed to me so menacing, I
turned my steps to meet the ancient
poet. He moved ahead and as we made our
way, he said to me, "Why are you so
dismayed?" I satisfied him, answering
him fully. And then that sta sage
exhorted me, remember the words that
have been spoken here against you. Now
pay attention, and he raised his finger.
When you shall stand before the gentle
splendor of one whose gracious eyes see
everything, then you shall learn from
her your lifetime's journey. Following
that his steps turn to the left, leaving
the wall and moving toward the middle
along a path that strikes into a valley
whose stench as it rose up disgusted us.
>> Okay, so you know, uh Virgil sees the
anguish in Dante's
uh face. And so Virgil asks, "What's
wrong?" And Don explains, "Well, because
I lied to uh Kante and told him his son
was dead." And Virgil is like, "Focus on
your mission, Dante." Okay. You You are
You are about to meet Beatric. Focus on
that. All right. All right. Let's go to
11, please.
[snorts]
KTO 11.
Along the upper rim of a high bank
formed by a ring of massive broken
boulders, we came above a crowd more
cruy pent. And here, because of the
outrageous stench thrown up in excess by
that deep abyss, we drew back till we
were behind the lid of a great tomb on
which I made out this inscribed. I hold
Pope Anastasius enticed to leave the
true path by Fotinis. It would be better
to delay desens so that our senses may
grow somewhat used to this foul stench
and then we can ignore it. So said my
master, and I answered him, do find some
compensation lest this time be lost. And
he, you see, I've thought of that, my
son. Within this ring of broken rocks,
he then began, there are three smaller
circles like those that you're leaving,
they range down. Those circles are all
full of cursed spirits so that your
seeing of them may suffice. Learn how.
Learn now the how and why of their
confinement. A very malice that earns
hate in heaven. Injustice is the end.
And each such end by force or fraud
brings harm to other men. However, fraud
is man's peculiar vice. God finds it
more displeasing and therefore the
fraudulent or lower suffering more.
>> Okay. So they're descending down to hell
and uh they will first enter the circle
of violence and there are three
different types of violence. Okay,
violence against others, violence
against yourself, suicide, and violence
against God. Okay, that's the uh circle
of violence. And then they'll go even
further down to the circle of fraud.
Okay, so uh what Virgil tells Dante is
that fraud is worse than violence.
Can someone guess why that'd be the
case? Why would in Dante's
framework fraud is worse than violence?
Like violence is like you kill someone,
right? But what's fraud?
Fraud is you lie to someone. What? What?
Why is that different? Yes.
because fraud impacts the imagination of
someone and you like like destroy a part
of their reality for like to something
that's not even true. So when you when
you kill someone, they're dead. But when
you when you like lie to someone, you
kill their perception of reality, which
is even worse because they can't
experience life as it is, but they
[clears throat] like have to live up to
a lie.
>> Exactly. Exactly correct. Yes. Okay. So,
did did you want to add add to that or
>> Okay. All right. So, again, the
framework, right? Donnie wants us to
live a life of faith, hope, and love.
But for that to happen, you have to have
faith. But if people are lying to you
all the time, right, or people are
cheating you all the time, that makes
you question reality itself. That that
that makes you question your own faith.
And so that's problematic. Okay. Whereas
if someone does violence to you, it's
like, well, you know, the guy's an
or whatever. Okay.
Okay. Let's let's keep on going.
[snorts]
>> Line 28. The violent take all of the
first circle. But since one uses force
against three persons, that circle's
built of three divided rings. To God and
to oneself and to one's neighbor, I mean
to them or what is theirs, one can do
violence, as you shall now hear clearly.
Violent death and painful wounds may be
inflicted on one's neighbor. His
possessions may suffer ruin, fire, and
extortion. Thus murderers and those who
strike and malice, as well as plunderers
and robbers. These in separated ranks
the first ring racks. A man can set
violent hands against himself or his
belongings. So within the second ring
repents, though uselessly whoever would
deny himself your world, gambling away,
wasting his patrimony and weeping where
he should instead be hap be happy.
One can be violent against the godhead
one's heart denying blaspheming him and
scorning nature and be good and the good
in her. So with it with with sign the
smallest ring has sealed both Sodom and
Cahords and all those who speak in
passionate contempt of God. Now fraud
that eats away at every conscience is
practiced by a man against another who
trusts in him or one who has no trust.
This latter way seems only to cut off
the bond of love that nature forges.
Thus nestled within the second circle.
>> Okay. So again here explains it right.
The problem with fraud is it destroys
people's capacity to trust. Without
trust, there can be no love. Okay?
That's why it's worse than violence.
Okay. Uh, keep on going.
Line 58.
Hypocrisy and flattery, sorcerers and
falsifier, Simeon theft, and bariters
and panders and like trash. And in the
former way of fraud, not only the love
that nature forges is forgotten, but
added love that builds a special trust.
Thus in the tightest circle where there
is the universe's center, seed of this,
all traitors are consumed eternally.
Master, your reasoning is clear indeed.
I said, it has made plain for me the
nature of this pit and the population in
it. But tell me, those the dense marsh
holds or those driven before the wind or
those on whom rain falls or those who
clash with such harsh tongues, why are
they not all punished in the city of
flaming red if God is angry with them?
And if he's not, why then are they
tormented?
>> Okay. Right. So, okay. So, the last
three major circles are fraud,
uh, sorry, violence, fraud, and
treachery. Why is treachery the worst
possible sin?
Uh yes,
>> because uh societywide uh treachery will
have knock on effects because if you're
treacherous to someone else, then
they're more likely to do it to someone
else and
>> Exactly.
>> destroys society.
>> Exactly. That's the idea here, right?
Where love is a virtuous circle, but
treachery is a vicious circle. If you're
betrayed by someone else, your first
instinct is to betray another person,
right? It's a chain of events. That's
why treachery is the worst possible
because it is altering the very fabric
of reality itself. Okay? Fraud distorts
your perception of reality. It it makes
you misperceive reality, but treachery
makes you want to shape reality against
God. And that's why it's the worst
possible sin. Okay? Does that make
sense? All right. Let's let's keep
going. [snorts]
>> Line 76.
And then to me, why does your reason
wander so far from its accustomed
course? He said, "Or of what other
things are you now thinking? Have you
forgotten then the words with which your
ethics treats of those three
dispositions that strikes at heaven's
will? Incontinence of malice and mad
beiality, and how the fault that is the
least condemned and least offense God is
incontinence." If you consider carefully
this judgment and call to mind the souls
of upper hell who bear their penalties
outside the city, you'll see why they
have been set off from these unrighteous
ones and why when heavens mentions
hammers at them, it carries lesser
anger.
>> Okay, so Don is asking him like why is
hell partitioned in this way? And uh
Virgil says well because of
incontinence, malice and madiality.
Okay, incontinence is basically you're
not taking yourself seriously. you lack
will, right? That's why um lust and uh
wrath and greed and gluttony are outside
of the capital city, okay? They're not
that serious. You're just doing harm to
yourself. Whereas uh if you go to if you
go go into this and you see heresy and
fraud, it's malice to other people.
Okay? That's why they have to be
punished separately. Okay? Let's keep on
going.
91 Oh son that heals all sight that is
perplexed when I ask you your answer so
contents that doubting pleases me as
much as knowing go back a little to that
point I said where you told me that
usery offense divine goodness unravel
now that not philosophy for one who
understands points out and not just in
one place he said how nature follows as
she takes her course the divine
intellect and divine art if you read
your and if you read your physics
carefully not many pages from the start
you'll see that when it can your art
will follow nature just as a pupil
imitates his master so that your art is
almost God's grandchild from these two
art and nature it is fitting if you
recall how Genesis begins for men to
make their way to gain their living and
since the user prefers another pathway
he scorns both nature and herself and
art her follower his hope is elsewhere
but follow me for it is time to move the
fishes glitter now on the horizon all
the way spread out over chorus
Only beyond can one climb down the
cliff.
>> Why are money mon money lenders
punished? Why are usurers punished? Why
are bankers punished?
And and Dante comes from a banking
family by the way, right? His father was
a money lender.
Why are what's the problem with with
with users? Yes.
>> Um maybe because fraud. Because the
banker always try to keep telling lie.
>> No, no, it's not fraud. It's something
else. What what is I think in the Bible
it was a sin to lend money and
everything because it doesn't produce
any actual good. It's like using money
to make money. So you don't actually pay
or work hard, you know, to earn your
money.
>> Right. Exactly. Okay. So do you
understand this idea, right? Faith,
hope, and love is that you are part of
the creation process. You are
co-creative with God. But with money
lending, you're charging interest. So
you are basically exploiting other
people's capacity to co-create with God.
You're not doing anything. You're just
charging interest. Does that make sense?
That uh did did Yes.
>> So I I my initial guess was that it was
related to like the the Jewish ability
to lend money where the Christian had a
prohibition against it. But I you just
said that Dante's family were money
lenders. So can you reconcile the
difference that Dant is now committing
his father to hell essentially?
>> Um yeah. So this is like really
interesting. Okay, but if you contrast
uh if you just look at everyone from
Donny's life, okay, the vast majority of
them are actually in hell. Okay, some of
them in purgatory. There's exactly one
his great-grandfather who is in heaven.
And that's a great thing about Dante,
right? He's like, don't think about
family. Don't think about friends. Think
about God's justice. Think about what
God's will is. think about things
objectively and if you can go beyond
faction if you go can go beyond family
then God's reasoning will make sense to
you yes
>> I think that's what um Jesus also
preached him he told all his disciples
that they should all leave their
families behind and start a new life
where they are not bound to their yeah
>> right and like if you think about the
greatest act of faith hope and love at
this time in history is to leave your
family behind. Right. Because like at
this time the only thing you can depend
on is your family. Right. So, so, so
what both Jesus and D are saying is live
a life of justice and God will support
you. Okay. And that's a life of faith,
love, and hope. Okay. All right. All
right. Let's let's keep on going.
Conto 12.
The place that we had reached for our
descent along the bank was alpine. What
reclined upon that bank would too repel
all eyes just like the toppled mass of
rock that struck because of earthquake
or eroded props. the adage on its flank,
the side of Trent, where from the
mountain top from which it thrusts down
to the plain the rock is shattered so
that it permits a path for those above.
Such was the passage down to that ravine
and at the edge of above the cracked
abyss. There lay outstretched the infamy
of Cree, conceived within the
counterfeited cow, and catching sight of
us, he bit himself like one whom fury
devastates within. Turning to him, my
sage cried out, "Perhaps you think this
is the Duke of Athens here, who in the
world above brought you, oh your death,
be off, you beast. This man who comes
has not been tutored by your sister. All
he wants is coming here is to observe
your torment."
>> So, this is the the monitor, and of
course, the person who kills the monitor
is Thesius, who becomes the first king
of of Athens. Okay. Um, that that's just
a a mythological reference. Uh, it
doesn't really matter for the story.
Keep on going. Line 22.
Just as the bull that breaks loose from
its halter the moment it receives the
fatal stroke and cannot run but plunges
back and forth, so did I see the minur
respond, and my alert guide cried, "Run
toward the pass. It's better to descend
while he's berserk." And so we made our
way across that heap of stones which
often moved my feet because my weight
was somewhat strange for them. While
climbing down, I thought, he said, "You
wonder perhaps about that fallen mass
watched over by the inhuman rage I have
just quenched. Now I would have you know
the other time that I descended into
lower hell, this mass of boulders had
not yet collapsed. But if I reason
rightly, it was just before the coming
of the one who took from d the highest
circle of splendid spoils that on all
sides the steep and filthy valley had
trembled so I thought the universe felt
love by which as some believe the world
has often been converted into chaos. And
at that moment here as well as elsewhere
these ancient boulders toppled in this
way.
But fix your eyes below upon the valley
for now we're near the stream of blood
where those who injure others violently
boil. Oh, blind cupidity and insane
anger which goed us on so much in our
short life, then steep us in such grief
eternally. I saw a broad ditch bent into
an arc so that it would it could embrace
all of that plain precisely as my guide
had said before. Between it and the base
of the embankment raised files of
centaurs who were armed with arrows, as
in that world above, they used hunt. On
seeing as they all rained in, and after
they had chosen boughs and shafts, three
of their number moved out from their
ranks, and so far off one cried, "What
punishment do you approach as you
descent the slope, but speak from here?
If not, I draw my bow." My master told
him, "We shall make reply only to
Shiron. When we reach a side, your hasty
will has never served you well." Then he
nudged me and said, "That one is Nessus,
who died because of lovely Dionaura, and
of himself wrought vengeance for
himself."
In the middle, gazing at his chest, is
mighty Chiron, tutor of Achilles. The
third is Fus, he who was so frenzied,
and many thousands wheeled around the
moat, their arrows aimed at any soul
that thrusts above the blood more than
its guilt allotss.
By now we had drawn near those agile
beasts. Jon drew out an arrow with the
notch. He part of his beard back upon
his jaws. When he uncovered his enormous
mouth, he said to his companions, "Have
you noticed how he who walks behind
moves what he touches?" Dead souls are
not accustomed to do that. And my good
guide, now near the centaur's chest, the
place where his two natures met,
replied,
"He indeed alive, and so alone it falls
to me to show him the dark valley.
Necessity has brought him here, not
pleasure. For she he who gave me this
new task was one who had just come from
singing Hallelujah. He's no robber. I'm
not a thief. But by the power that
permits my steps to journey on so wild a
path, give us one of your band to serve
as our companion, and let him show us
where to forth the ditch. And let him
bear this man upon his back, for he's no
spirit who can fly through air." Then
Sharon wheeled about and right and said
to Nessus, "Then return and be their
guide. If other troops disturb you, fend
them off." Now with our faithful escort,
we advanced along the blood red boiling
ditches banks beside the piercing cries
of those who boiled. I saw some who were
sunk up to their brows and that huge
centur said, "These are the tyrants who
plunged their hands in blood and
plundering. Here they lament their
ruthless crimes. cured both Alexander
and the fierce Dian um Dagius who
brought such years of grief to Sicily.
That brow with hair so black as Elino
that other there the blonde one is Oo
Veste who was indeed undone was in the
world above by his fierce son.
>> Okay. All right. So um they are in the
first um place of violence and these
these are people who commit violence
against others and for their and so for
their sin what's happening is that they
bo they are drowning in a boiling uh
lake okay and they ever try to get out
of it centers come and shoot arrows at
them okay that's that's what they've
done to other people okay now inside
this uh boiling lake is Alexand the
great
What's problematic about this? Why why
this be paradoxical?
[clears throat]
What's the paradox here? When you think
of a great, who else do you think of?
>> Genghask Khan.
>> Genghask Khan. Who else?
>> Napoleon.
>> Napoleon. Who else?
>> Hitler.
>> Okay, guys. Guys, this is year 1300.
Okay, so let's go too far. They don't
even know who Gangask Khan is at at this
time. Right? But I'm saying like in year
1300, if you think of Alexander the
Great, who do you think of?
>> Caesar.
>> Julius Caesar, right? Where's Julius
Caesar?
He's in limbo. I don't understand what's
going on here. Where's Alexander the
Great in the circle of violence, but
Julius Caesar is in limbo.
They did the same thing, right? They're
both great conquerors. They killed a lot
of people for their own personal glory.
Why would the great be in
here the circle of violence and the
Julius Caesar is like in limbo? Why
would that happen?
Yes. I mean my guess is
like if Dante has Virgil as his guide,
Virgil cannot like see Caesar in heaven
because Virgil was appointed by Augustus
um the adopted son of Julius Caesar to
write the iniad. Right. So like if he
like sees Julius Caesar head in in the
like one of the worst circles and that'
be like pretty problematic.
>> Exactly. Okay. Yeah. Right. Because if
Virgil
um is the great poet and we will learn
in paradise that the Roman Empire is
what gives rise to Catholic Church and
is part of God's will. Yeah, then it
makes sense to put Julius Caesar in um
limbo. But this raises another question.
Where's Augustus Caesar?
Okay. We we ask Chhat BT. Let's let's
ask Chhat BT. All right.
Just just just just just Google this.
Like where is Augusta Caesar in
the Divine Comedy? Oh, wait, wait.
Sorry. Before we we do this, can you
guess where where he'd be?
Yes.
Not lower, right? Because who's more
important, Julius Caesar, or Augustus
Caesar? True.
>> I would think Augustus Caesar because
Augustus Caesar is the one who who who
created the Roman Empire, right? Which
then becomes a Catholic church.
So where should he be?
At least purgatory, at least limbo,
possibly even paradise, right? But let's
let's figure this out. Okay, again,
logically speaking, we just extend
extend your logic, right? He should be
somewhere nice, whether it's limbo or
purgatory or even paradise. Where where
is where? But where's Argus Caesar
located in divine comedy?
Does he appear?
August Caesar is one of the most
important historical figures, right? The
greatest emperor of Rome, the man who
created the Roman Empire.
Where is he?
>> I think he's in limbo.
>> No, no, no, no, no. I'm asking you where
in the divine comedy is. If we're
looking for divine comedy, where can we
find our guesses Caesar?
>> Uh, in uh KTO one, I think.
>> Does
No, I'm saying physically like where
where is he situated?
Where does purgatory?
We see Julius Caesar in limbo. We know
he's there. We see Socrates in limbo. We
know he's there. We see a great being
burned alive
in the circle of violence. We know he is
there. But where is our Caesar
physically in Divine Comedy?
He's nowhere guys. He does not exist
physically in the nine comedy but he
does he is referenced in the nine comics
by who? Virgil
>> Virgil is what keeps the memory of
August Caesar alive. But August Caesar
has disappeared
right so this is a huge problem. We know
Alexander the Great because uh it's
written here he is burned in circle of
violence. We know Julius Caesar is in
limbo.
We don't know where Gar Caesar is. And
the only time August Caesar is mentioned
it's because Virgil speaks him out.
Right? It's only Virgil that's keeping
keeping alive the August of Caesar.
This is very confusing, right? Okay. So
again, it's meant So the subversive
comedy first and foremost, it's meant to
be subversive. It's meant to undermine
our traditional understanding
all things.
Okay. So, do you think how do you think
Donnie feels about Augusta Caesar?
>> Well, just
can you explain?
>> Conflicted. The only reason I can think
of that he's not there other than when
Virgil mentions him is
Dante cannot decide where to place him.
>> Yes. [clears throat] I mean during
Augustus Jesus was killed.
>> Yes.
>> Was it Augustus? No, it was not
Augustus. It was Tiberius.
>> Oh, was it not Dorian?
>> Yeah, it was Tiberious.
>> Oh, okay. Tiberious. Yeah. But but it
was during Augustus that Ces that Jesus
was born, right? And what the Catholic
Church teaches you is that without the
without Augustus
um
didn't Jesus could not have been born
and the way could have been paid for the
for Christianity to arise. Okay. So
Jesus was killed during Jesus was killed
during Tiberius and um Jesus was born
Augustus.
Okay.
Yes.
>> I think like Dante naturally don't like
uh Augustus because it's uh cuz August
is the one who ordered Virgil to write
the Ania, right? And it's also August
the one who promotes piety which is what
Dante like disagree with.
>> Right. So [clears throat] uh so the
greatest
um act of faith, love and hope is
poetry, right? Virgil is a divine po
prophet, divine poet. That's how he's
able to do this because God willed it.
So
Augustus Caesar, what he did was he took
this gift of poetry which is divine. He
corrupted it to serve the ends of
empire.
And that's why Augustus is not mentioned
or sorry he's not he's mentioned but
he's not he's not given a place in the
divine comedy because what Donnie has
done is he has he has a he has basically
cast him to to a place worse than hell
which is annihilation.
Okay. He is beyond the universe. God has
forgotten him. God has cast him away
from this universe. There can be
absolutely no redemption for him. Okay?
God wants to forget about him because
his crime was so great. It is the
greatest crime in the world to try to
corrupt the message of God to serve your
own political ends.
Does that make sense, guys?
Because like again, you have to explain
to me where Augustus is. He's not in
Divine Comedy. And [snorts] he is one of
the most important historical figures
ever in in history. Uh yes.
>> But isn't Virgil then like a I mean he's
part of this, right? Because he wrote it
down like he could refuse to write down
this poetry that goes against God. So I
mean
>> Right. And that's why Virgil is in hell,
right?
>> But he's only in limbo.
>> Um
right. But he he's still he's still in
in hell. Right. Okay. And and also like
remember what Don is trying to do is
he's trying to awaken the reader. You
understand? Because at this time in
history, everyone is reading uh the
Iniad. Everyone loves the Iniad because,
you know, you're sort of forced to love
the Iniad. And so he needs to take
people away from the Iniad. It has to be
a process of slow discovery, okay? An
epiphany where Virgil is probably the
villain here. Okay? and and as we go on
we'll we'll we'll recognize this but not
at this stage. Okay, does that make
sense? It's a journey. Okay. It's not
only Dy's journey from sin into virtue,
but it's also our journey from ignor
from the darkness into the light. Okay.
All right. Does it make sense, guys? All
right. Let let let's let's keep on
going.
Line 115. A little farther on, the
centaur stopped above a group that
seemed to rise above the boiling blood
as far up as their throats. He pointed
out one shade alone apart and said,
"Within God's bosom. He impaled the
heart that still drips blood upon the
temps. Then I got caught sight of some
who kept their heads and even their full
chests above the tide. Among them many
whom I recognized, and so the blood
grew, always sat shallower until it only
scorched the feet. And he here we found
a place where we could forge a ditch.
poured a ditch. The ditch just as you
see that on this side the brook
continually thins. The centaur said, "So
I should have you know the rivlet along
the other side will slowly deepen its
bed until it reaches once again the
depth where tyranny must make lament.
And there divine justice torments at he
who was such a scourge upon the earth
and pira sexist to eternity. It milks
the tears that boiling brook and locks
from reneer of cornetto reneer pots.
those two who waged such war upon the
high roads. Then he turned around and
crossed the fort again.
>> Okay. [clears throat]
Conto 13. Nessus had not yet reached the
other bank when we began to make our way
across a wood on which no path had left
its mark. No green leaves in that
forest, only black. No branches straight
and smooth but nodded gnarled. No fruits
were there but breers bearing poison.
Even those savage beasts that roam
between Suchina and Cornetto. Beasts
that hate tilled lands do not have ps
and dense. This the nesting place of the
foul harpies who chase the Trojans from
the states
um states with sad foretelling of their
future trials. Their wings are wide,
their necks and faces human, their feet
are talent, their great bellies
feathered. They utter their laments on
the strange trees. And my can and my
kind master then instructed me, before
you enter farther, know that now you're
within the second ring and shall be here
until you reach the horde of sand.
Therefore, look carefully. You'll see
such things as would deprive my speech
of all belief. From every side I heard
the sound of cries, but I could not see
any source for them. So that in my
bewilderment I stopped. I think that he
was thinking that I thought so many
voices moaned among those trunks from
people who had been concealed from us.
Therefore my master said, "If you would
tear a little twig from many of these
plants, the thoughts you have will also
be cut off." Then I stretch out my hand
a little way and from a great thorn bush
snapped off a branch at which its trunk
cried out, "Why do you tear me?" And
then when it had grown more dark with
blood asked again, "Why do you break me
off? Are you without all sentiment of
pity? We once were men and now are arid
stumps. Your hand might well have shown
us greater mercy had we been nothing
more than souls of serpents.
As from a sapling log that catches fire
along one of its ends, while at the
other it drips and hisses with escaping
vapor, so from that broken stump issued
together both words and blood at which I
let the branch fall, and I stood like
one who's afraid. My sage said, "Winded
soul, if earlier he had been able to
believe what he had only glimpsed within
my poetry, then he would not have set
his hand against you. But its
incredibility made me urge him to do a
deed that grieves me deeply." But tell
me who you were, so that he may to make
amends, refresh your fame within the
world above, where he can still return.
To which the trunk, your sweet speech
draws me, so that I cannot be still, and
may not oppress you if I linger now in
talk. I'm the one who guarded both the
keys of Frederick's heart and turned
them, locking and unlocking them with
such dexterity that none but I could
share his confidence. And I was faithful
to my splendid office, so faithful that
I lost both sleep and strength. The
who never turned her harlot's eyes
away from Caesar's dwelling. She who is
the death of all and vice of every court
inflamed the minds of everyone against
me. And those inflamed then so inflamed
a gusted that my delight honors turned
to sadness.
My mind because of its sustainable
temper believing it could flee disdain
through death made me unjust against my
own just self. I swear to you by the
peculiar roots of this thorn bush. I
never broke my faith with him who was so
worthy with my lord. If one of you
returns into the world, then let him
help my memory which still lies prone
beneath the battering of envy.
>> Okay, so now we are in a forest and
these are people who have killed
themselves. They commit suicide. They've
committed no other sin but suicide.
Okay, and what's happened is they've
been transformed into trees. So they
don't take their bodies seriously. So
now their bodies are now just trees.
[clears throat] And what happens is that
the harpies come and uh eat the berries
that they grow. Okay, they feel this
eternal torment. Um and then Donnie
talks to one of these trees and um this
person is a person that Donnie knows as
well and he's a historical character and
he was a counselor to a king who was
accused of treason. He was virtuous. He
was talented. But uh once he was accused
of treason,
um he was innocent of treason, but he
kills himself in despair. Okay? Why
would this be a problem? Why would this
be a sin?
Why is suicide a sin?
>> Yes.
So firstly, you're abandoning all of
faith, hope, and love. Uh and secondly,
similarly to treachery, I think uh
societywide, it damages other people and
could therefore affect other people's
potential to love and connect in the
future.
>> Exactly. That's exactly correct. Yes.
First of all, you are supposed to live
live a life of faith, hope, and and
love. And this is the opposite, right?
Where you just don't believe in God
anymore. It's basically rejecting God
and says you know like this is so
hopeless even God can't save me. Okay.
The other thing is like you become a bad
role model to other people as well. You
show that you uh who is a very virtuous
talented person you of all people should
have faith hope and love and by
abandoning yourself you abandon God and
you abandon society as well. Okay. All
right. So thank you. Excellent. All
right. Let's keep on going.
[clears throat]
My mind, because of its distainable
temper, believing it could flee disdain
through death, made me unjust against my
own just self. I swear to you, by the
peculiar roots of this thorn bush, and
never broke my faith with him who was so
worthy with my lord. If one of you
returns into the world, then let him
help my memory, which still lies prone
beneath the battering of envy." The poet
waited briefly. Then he said to me,
"Since he's silent, do not lose this
chance, but speak and ask what you would
know." And I do you continue ask of him
whatever you believe I should request. I
cannot. So much pity takes my heart.
Then he began again. Imprisoned spirit.
So may this man do freely what you ask.
May it please you to tell us something
more of how the soul is bound into these
knots. And tell us if you can if anyone
can ever find his freedom from these
limbs. At this the trunk breathed
violently. Then that wind became this
voice. Ye shall be answered promptly
when the spa savage spirit quits the
body from which it has torn itself. Then
minnow sends it to the seventh mo. It
falls into the wood and there's no place
to which it is allotted. But wherever
fortune has flung that soul that is the
space where even as a grain of spelt it
sprouts. It rises as a sapling a wild
plant and then the harpies feeding on
his leaves cause pain and for that pain
provide a vent. Like other souls we
shall seek out the flesh that we have
left but none of us shall wear it. It is
not right for any man to have what he
himself has cast aside. We'll drag our
bodies here. They'll hang in this sad
wood each on the stump of its vindictive
shade.
And we were still intent upon the trunk
believing it had wanted to say more when
we were overtaken by a roar. Just as the
hunter is aware of chase and boar as
they draw near his post, he hears the
beast and then the branches as they
crack. And there upon the left were two
who scratched and naked fled so
violently that they tore away each
forest bow they passed. The one in front
now come death quickly come. The other
shade who thought himself as though was
shouting after him. Lano your legs were
not so nimble at the joust of Topo. And
then perhaps because he he'd lost his
breath he fell into one tangle with a
bush. Behind these two black
filled the wood and they were just as
eager and as swift as grey hounds that
have been let off their leash. They set
their teeth in him where he had
crouched. And piece by piece those dogs
dismembered him and carried off his
miserable limbs. Then he who was my
escort took my hand. He led me to the
lacerated thorn that wept in vain where
it was bleeding broken. Oh Yakapo, it
said it said the Santo Andrea, what have
you gained by using me a screen? Am I to
blame for your indecent life? When my
good master stood beside that bush, he
said, "Who are you who through many
wounds must breathe with blood your
melancholy words?" And he to us, "Of
spirits who have come to witness the
outrageous laceration that leaves so
many of my branches torn,
collect them at the foot of the sad
thorn. My home was in the city whose
first patron gave away to John the
Baptist. For this reason, he'll always
use his art to make it sorrow. And if
along the crossing of the Arno, some
effigy of Mars had not remained, the
citizens who afterward rebuilt their
city on the ashes that till I had left
them left to them would have travailed
in vain. I made of my own house my
gallows place.
>> Okay, let's move on to count of 14. I'm
sorry we're moving too fast, okay? But
again, um we're trying to finish the
line comedy and we're trying to develop
the major themes of it. Okay, so um the
next few ktos are extremely important.
Uh, and here again we're trying to
figure out what is wrong with Florence.
Okay. Um,
>> conto 14. Love of our native city
overcame me. I gathered up the scattered
boughs and gave them back to him whose
voice was spent already. From there we
reached the boundary that divided the
second from the third ring and the sight
of a dread work that justice had
devised. To make these strange things
clear, I must explain that we had come
upon an upon an open plain that banished
all green things from its bed. The wood
of sorrow was a garland around it, just
as that wood is ringed by a sad channel.
Here at the very edge we stayed our
steps. The ground was made of sand, dry
and compact, a sand not different in
kind from that on which the feet of Ko
had once tramped. Oh vengeance of the
Lord, how you should be dreaded by
everyone who now can read whatever was
made manifest to me. I saw so many
flocks of naked souls all weeping
miserably and it seemed that they were
ruled by different decrees. Some lay
upon the ground flat on their back. Some
huddled in a crouch and there they sat
and others moved about incessantly. The
largest group was those who walked
about. The smallest those supine in
punishment, but these had loose their
tongues to tell their torment. Above
that plain of sand, distended flakes of
fire showered down. Their fall was slow
as snow descends on Alps when no wind
blows. Just like the flames that
Alexander saw in India's hot zones where
fire when fires fell intact into the
ground on his battalions for which
wisely he had his soldiers the
soil to see that every fire was spent
before new flames were added to the old.
So did the neverending heat descend.
With this the sand was kindled just as
tinder on meaning flint will flame
doubling the pain.
The dance of wretched hands was never
done. Now here, now there they tried to
beat aside the fresh flames as they
fell. And it began to speak. My master,
are you who can defeat all things except
for those tenacious demons who tried to
block us at the entryway? Who that giant
there who does not seem to heed singing?
He who lies in scorns and scowls. He
whom the rains can't seem to soften. And
he himself on noticing that I was
quering my guide about him cried that
which I was in life. in death through
hov where out the smith from whom he
took and wrath the keenged thunderbolt
with it with which on my last day I was
to be transfixed
and if he tire the others one by one in
Montibello at the studio forge while
bellowing oh help good Vulcan help just
as he did when there was war at Flegra
and cast his shafts at me with all his
force not even then would he have happy
vengeance
then did my guide speak with such vehe
arguments that I had never heard him use
before.
Oh, Capanas, for your arrogance that is
not quenched, you're punished all the
more. No torture other than your own
madness could offer pain enough to match
your wrath. But then, with gentler face,
he turned to me and said, "That man was
one of seven kings besieging thieves."
He held and still, it seems, holds God
in great disdain, despising him. But as
I told him now, his maladiction stood
well as honor ornaments upon his chest.
And now follow me and take care. Do not
set your feet upon the sand that's
burning hot, but always keep them back
close to the forest. In silence we had
reached a place where flowed a slender
water course out of the wood. A stream
whose redness makes me shudder still. As
from bulock came pours a brook whose
waters then are shared by prostitutes.
So did the stream run down across the
sand. Its bed and both its banks were
made of stone together with the slopes
along its shores. so that I saw a
passageway lay there.
Among all other things that I have shown
you since we first made our way across
the gate, whose threshold is forbidden
to no one, no thing has yet been
witnessed by your eyes as notable as
this bread reveal it which quenches
every flame that burns above it. These
words were spoken by my guide. At this I
begged him to bestow the food for which
he had already given me the craving. A
devastated land lies in midsea, a land
that is called Cree, he answered me.
Under its king, the world once lived
chastely. Within that land there was a
mountain blessed with leaves and waters,
and they called it Ida. But it is
withered now like some old thing. It
once was chosen as a trusted grad for
Ria for her son to hide him better. When
he cried out, she had her servants
clamor. Within the mountain is a huge
old man who stands erect, his back
turned toward Damietta, and looks at
Rome as if it were his mirror.
The old man's head is fashioned of fine
gold. The pure silver forms his arms and
chest, but he is made of brass down to
the cleft. Below that point, he's of
choicest iron except for his right foot,
made of baked clay, and he rests more on
this than on the left. Each part of him
makes up the gold is cracked. And down
that fissure there are tears that drip.
When gathered, they pierce through that
cavern's floor. And crossing rocks into
this valley from Acron and sticks to
flag.
And then they make their way down this
tight channel. And at the point past
which there's no descent, they form
Coxitus.
Since you're to see what that pool is,
I'll not describe it here. And I asked
him, "But if the rivlet must follow such
a course down from our world, why can we
see it only at its boundary?" And he to
me, "You know this place is round, and
though the way that you have come is
long and always toward the left and
toward the bottom, you still have not
completed all the circles, so that if
something new appears to us, it need not
bring such wonder to your face." And I
again, Master, where's flesh thorn and
where's leaf? You omit the second and
say this rain of tears has formed the
first. I'm pleased indeed, he said, with
all your questions. Yet one of them
might well have found its answer ready
when you saw the red stream boiling. You
shall see. But past this abyss there
where the spirits go to cleanse
themselves where their repented guilt is
set aside. Then he declared, "The time
has come to quit this wood. See that you
follow close behind me. These margins
form a path that does not scorch and
over them all flaming vapor is quenched.
>> Okay. All right. So, two comments. Okay.
The first comment is that clearly the
geography of hell really matters. Okay.
If Donnie is going to spend a lot of
time describing how these rivers flow,
um how hell is constructed the way it
is, then it clearly matters. But again,
I don't have the knowledge of the
occult, of rituals, of magic to fully
appreciate why this matters. Okay.
Clearly, if you visualize this, there is
symbology at work, right? Um um at this
time in history, it's very common for
people to engage in magic. Basically,
using symbols, using chants, using
rituals in order to summon angels, to
summon demons. Um, and if you were to
again draw this out, um, if you were
actually to act this out, then it's all
then that gives you insight into how
these things work. Uh, but again, I'm
not I I don't have any expertise in
symbology, in the occult, in magic. I I
don't I don't have to comment. Okay? So,
if you really want to understand Dante,
then you then you need to do a lot more
research into the occult. That's point
one. Point two is what is strange about
this KTO is for the first time we are
meeting a nonhuman
who's being punished. Right? Throughout
the inferno, we met humans and they
could be myth mythological or real, but
they're being punished. And for the
first time, we are meeting a non-human,
a giant who's being punished. And how
and what is his reaction to being
punished? And and in in this and in this
pun and then in this it's uh violence
against God. Everyone's running. There's
like um fire uh and brimstone being held
being being rained down on them. Okay.
So, they're trying to dodge all these
missiles. And how and how does this
giant feel about all this? Anyone? What
is his reaction?
>> He's crying.
>> He's not crying.
>> He's happy, right? He or rather he's
trying to appear chill.
>> Yeah. He doesn't care, right? So So
what's the message here? You have a
giant who's like, "Ah, whatever, man.
Like missiles are being uh rained on me.
I don't care. Who cares?" And the other
humans and the others are like dodging.
the humans are dodging or running away.
Um, what's going on here?
And again, this is the only time when we
have a nonhuman human being punished and
the entire scene is like he's just
complete apathy
and Virgil says, "Oh, you're so
arrogant." What's the message here?
>> [snorts]
>> Uh yes,
>> I just guessed maybe the great men they
they want the people who care about them
but uh Ding do not care about him. It
means that they're nothing. So maybe
this cry punishment for for those great
guy who think they're great but actually
they're not.
>> Yes. Yes.
Um maybe because hell should only impact
humans. Um you know because the human is
seen or Dant sees the human as the um
middle of the universe basically the
Yeah. So
God doesn't really care about giants. He
cares about humans more.
>> So what is the function of hell? Why
does hell exist?
to force reflection.
>> Yes. Okay. So, what's going on here is
if you just analyze the text, what what
is suggesting is that only we humans can
be punished
because only we humans can create path
to redemption. Okay, does that make
sense? The giant will not be redeemed.
He doesn't really care, right? But we we
we are being punished because at the
very heart of who we are, we are divine
spark that can never be extinguished. So
even though it feels hopeless, even
though you give up hope, there's still
that spark in you. And that's why you're
being punished to force reflection to
force you to recognize divine spark in
you. That's why the punishments are
constructed the way they are to show you
what your sin has caused to show you to
visualize the sin for you. Okay. All
right. And again, um, when Virgil talks
to these people, when when what they
always say is talk to Dante so that he
will write about you, so that he will be
remembered. Okay? And so even though you
think you are in hell, remember there
are still people who remember who you
are. And that is your path to
redemption, right? The fact that
regardless of how low you've sunk,
remember there's still people who
remember you. there's still people who
love you and once you believe that that
is your path to redemption and
salvation. Okay. So for Donna what's
really important to understand is that
we are our own redemption and salvation.
Okay. Any more
any questions or comments?
All right. Let's let's let's move on.
Okay. [snorts]
This is KTO this is Kanto 15 of Inferno.
KTO 15.
Now one of the hard borders bears us
forward. The river mist forms shadows
overhead and shields the shores and
water from the fire.
>> Just as between Wist and Bruge, the
Flemings in terror of the tide that
floods toward them have built a wall
dyes to daunt the sea. And as the
paduans along the Brena built bull works
to defend their towns and castles before
the dark days fall on Carantana,
just so were these embankments, even
though they were not built so high and
not so broad, whoever was the artisan
who made them.
>> Okay. So here in these in these um
lines, what Don is revealing is that the
geography of hell matches that of the
geography of Italy. Okay. Right. So, so
this is clearly he's trying to say that
this hell that that I that I am
describing to you, I'm actually
describing Italy at this point in
history. Okay. Uh, keep on going.
>> By now, we were so distant from the wood
that I should not have made out where it
was, not even if I turned around to
look. When we came on, a company of
spirits who made their way along the
bank, and each stared steadily at us as
in the dusk beneath the new moon, men
look at each other. They need their they
knit their brows and squinted at us just
as an old sailor at his needle's eye.
And when that family looked harder, I
was recognized by one who took me by the
hem and cried out, "This is marvelous."
That spirit having stretched his arm
toward me, I fixed my eyes upon his big
brown feature, so that the scorching of
his face could not prevent my mind from
recognizing him. And luring my face to
meet his face, I answered him, "Are you
here, Sarah Brunetto?" And he, "My son,
do not mind if Bernetto Latino langers
for a while with you and let the file
lets the file he's with pass on ahead."
>> Okay. Okay. So, this is a very important
passage in the vineyard. Okay. So, let
me explain what's going on. They are in
um the circle of violence and these are
this is like the worst people. These are
people who committed violence against
God and nature. Okay. And so the main
crime is homosexuality basically. Salami
and Sir Bernto is very important because
he's essentially
Dante's teacher and father. Okay. This
is a person that is dear to Donniey's
heart. Only Beatrice is actually more
dear to Dante than Sir Bernato. And you
can see in their words how affectionate
they are towards each other. So Sir
Bernetto, he uh is a homosexual. He's
condemned to the circle and he's running
with other homosexuals in the circle.
And the thing is if you stop, if you
ever lie down, you rest, you're
condemned even more. Okay? So what he's
saying is like Dante, I love you so
much. I'm going to stop and be punished
even more so I can talk to you. Right?
So this is showing the affection between
Sir Brunetto
and
Dante. But this raises a really huge
problem for us.
Does Dante really think homosexuality is
a problem? It's a sin.
Right. This is does really believe this?
So again, this is Serento, the person
that Donnie loves um like a father and
supernetto loves him like a son.
And they've they've always been very
close. And you would imagine that Dante
would put him in either purgatory or in
paradise.
And he doesn't do that. He puts him in
inferno. But not only that, but he puts
but Super Bernetto was a virtuous person
who who really only who only did one
thing which is like he was a homosexual.
That was that was it. Okay. That that
was the extent of his sin. And for that
and for that only he's condemned to run
around with other homosexuals for all of
eternity.
Okay, this is a huge paradox.
Uh yes.
>> I think it's because homosexuality
cannot bear children. And so in that
sense, you don't have the hope for the
future because you don't have a future
generation to remember you or to
contribute to the creation of God. And
so that's why sodomy is such a big sin.
>> Okay. And so how how would you
compensate for that? What did he do to
compensate for the fact that they didn't
have children? What did he do to show
that he had faith, hope, and love? Yes.
>> Through education
>> to me.
>> Through education.
>> Through education. What? And what else?
Can you guess his guess?
>> Well, he he taught Dante, right? So,
>> what did he teach Dante?
>> Faith, hope, and loss. I don't
>> like what was he teaching her off? Did
like like at this time in history? Huh?
>> Well, maybe poetry.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Right. He was a poet, right?
So, yeah. Okay. I understand. He doesn't
want to have children
and that shows his lack of faith, love,
and hope. But we already said that
poetry is always an expression of faith,
love, and hope.
Yes. Well, I think him being in hell
just shows that it isn't Dante who puts
him in hell, but it's the Catholic
Church, and the Catholic Church says
that homosexuality is a big sin. But
Dante wouldn't say that. So, it's not
him who puts people in hell, right? It's
the Catholic Church. But it's Don who
put Beatatrice in heaven.
Do you understand? So why would Donnie
do that? Why would Donnie put Beatatric
in heaven and then put his teacher, his
father figure in hell? And again,
I mean, the only crime, the only sin
that Superto is being accused of is
homosexuality. Yeah, he was a homosexual
sexuality, but do you really really
think Donnie cares that much about
homosexuality?
>> Yes. just it was a boundary you couldn't
cross and disagree with at the time and
so just like if he would just mention
that homosexuality was fine then his
work would have been destroyed.
>> Do you think homosexuality was common at
the time in history?
>> No, but it it occurred or in some text.
>> Okay, guys. Okay. I hate to say this.
Okay. All right. I I'm sorry. Um this
might get me bad on YouTube. Okay. But
if you look at every society, okay,
regardless if it's in China or Italy at
this time, if you look at the elite,
okay, I'm talking like like the
nobility, the elite, okay, homosexual
homosexual was really really common,
guys.
Really common.
Okay. You were not finding a society
where uh a welfare society where the
elite did not practice homosexuality in
some form. Yes. And especially during
the henistic period that it is actually
a greater
uh way to show your intellectual ability
to have another male partner than to
have a wife because a wife is
uneducated. You cannot have a soul to
soul talk with her but you could with a
younger boy. And so that's why uh yeah
the writer of uh the picture of Dorian
Gray um Oscar Wild really wanted that
kind of Yeah. because he expired to the
Greek.
>> So yeah. So right actually he's very
common among elite and
uh so what sato did he did nothing wrong
but just do what what all all the elite
did. Um not all the elite but like it
was pretty common man. It was really
common. Okay. Like like if you go to
like Yale. Okay. No. Yeah. Like Yeah.
Okay. But yeah, it's a common thing.
Okay. And among the elite it's not a big
deal. So again, we have to figure out
why this is happening. All right. Okay.
All right. So, uh we we'll do that after
the break. Okay. Welcome back. So, to
summarize what we learned um this
morning,
remember that Dante is a prophet. He's
basically trying to create an allegory
of hell
um to represent Italy, right? That's why
he's focused so much on the geography of
um hell. He's described in a way that if
you are Italian, you you just you just
like recognize the geography right away.
Um so hell as as a allegory for uh Italy
and we know that ultimately as a prophet
what Don is trying to convey to his um
audience is that you either repent or
you will be judged.
George judgment judge God's judgment
will be swift brutal and harsh and no
one listens. So 19 in 1357 came the
black death to wipe out around a third
of Europe uh even half of Europe at
certain places. [snorts] Um, and so what
what what we're trying to do is we're
trying to figure out how Dante perceived
his period at this time. And um there's
certain things about Florence
that made it unredeemable. Okay. And
what we're trying to figure out as well
is our time. Okay. Like today, do these
things apply to today? So the first
major characteristic about um hell is
it's factionalism right so whereas you
know Virgil is essentially the pope of
hell he is the author a authority figure
there are many factions who don't
actually listen to him there always
infighting going on so there's lot of
factionalism going on uh in Florence at
this time and the same is happening
today right where you have wars going on
right second major characteristic of
Florence is the intense economic
pressure
to succeed, right? All that matters is
success and achievement.
And today we call this the uh
meritocracy.
And in a meritocracy there are certain
things that become common and yet at the
same time there are inhumane. For
example, the most obvious is just to
apologize, right? So remember the scene
where um Dante lies to Kavakante and
says your son is dead and burning in
hell and he and it causes tremendous
despair to the father and Dante
recognizes he did wrong and rather than
apologize he runs away and tells someone
else to tell him on his behalf. Okay. So
there is um almost an incapacity to
apologize. So let me ask you this
question. Let's go back to the example
where at Chinua in the 80s or 90s um
there are two classmates who are good
friends, one gets in, the other receives
the envelope and rather than tell the
friend just throws the envelope in the
garbage.
Um and do you think that other person
ever apologize in her life?
Probably not. Okay, I'm guessing not.
But why why why can't she just
apologize?
>> Yes.
>> Cuz uh she probably has a huge ego and
she feel like she's she's um superior.
She she she should should be treated as
equal to the other person and she
justifies what what the her did. Yes.
>> Okay. Yes. Yes. Go ahead.
I mean, if she apologized, then the
other girl would know that she would
have gotten into Princeton in the first
place.
>> Well, well, eventually she found out,
right? Because this I'm I'm like, you
know, 20 years afterwards,
50 years afterwards, does she ever
apologize? Probably not. But why?
>> Yes.
Is like she she knows what she has done
is not it's evil. It's not good. And it
kind of like she's saying like, "Oh, I
know it's bad,
>> but it was evil, right?"
>> Yeah. But if she doesn't apologize,
it probably makes her feel better or
like I don't know.
>> Well,
go ahead. And then then, Carol. Yeah.
>> Um, maybe he can't Oh, maybe she can't
forgive herself,
>> so she can't uh forgive uh so she can't
uh say sorry to her roommate. Okay. Uh,
Carol,
>> I think she feels she's wronged in the
first place. So, why does she have to
apologize? She was wronged by the world.
>> Yeah. Okay. Yeah. So, the thing about um
I mean the meritocracy is that first of
all, you become the center of the world,
right? But also like you're keeping
score everywhere. Does it make sense?
So, not only do you care about the other
person's grades, but you also care about
hm does that person have a better house
than I than I than I do? Does a person
have better children than I do? You're
always keeping score, right? And one way
to keep score is how how much wrong did
you do, right? Everything everything is
is a test. Everything is a scorec card,
right? So, if I apologize, that means I
I'm I'm not in this person's debt. I now
owe him or her a favor, right? Rather
than seeing an apology as rectifying a
wrong, I see it as forcing myself to go
into someone's debt. Okay? It doesn't
make sense. Okay? And that's why people
don't apologize in a very um in a
meritocracy. But the other thing that's
even more troubling in a meritocracy is
and um it's you delight in others pain.
Okay, think about this where you know
you are at school and for
for the past year you delight in others
pain. Okay. So, for the past for this
entire year, there's one student in the
class, usually a girl, but she scores
100 on every single math test, right?
And you get like, I don't know, 80 85.
On the final test, on final exam, she
gets an 70. And she is distraught. She's
crying. She she's going berserk. How do
you feel?
No, you don't. [laughter] I put you on.
>> Maybe she cheated on a previous test.
>> No, no, but I'm saying what is your
emotion?
>> Oh,
>> yeah.
>> What is your emotion at this time?
>> Well, I mean, my emotion maybe depends
um how you act.
>> No, it doesn't. What? It does doesn't
depend who you are. Does depend how you
feel. What is your emotion?
>> I'll be like, "Finally, finally,
finally." Okay. Do you understand?
Finally. Okay. She finally failed.
Right. But every single day the teacher
is like, "Oh, she's the best in the
world and like just be like her." And
then she's finally screwed up. Okay, so
you delight in others pain. And we see
this in Divine Comedy where Dant is
crossing the river sticks, right? And
this is the um circle of wrath where
people are angry and they tear each
other apart. Um one of Dante's enemies
from real life, Filipio Argentina. He
falls into this lake and and there and
the other souls are tearing him apart.
Okay, literally tear him apart. And
Dante is ecstatic, right? So rather than
be like feel pity like great man. Okay.
And you know it's not a good look. But
what Donn is doing is he's trying to
reveal the problems and consequences of
a meritocracy. What a meritocracy
ultimately is. Imagine a race. Okay?
Imagine a race and everyone's running as
fast as they can. the person next to you
trips and falls and breaks his or her
ankle, right? What you should do as a
human being is stop and help that person
get up. But you don't. You just smile
and run on and you take in the light in
that other other person falling falling
down. And I mean, we live in China, we
see this every single day, right?
unfortunately where if you have if
you're a parent and you have kids, you
put your kids through this incredibly
harsh system,
right?
And you see your child unhappy and you
see your child um under a lot of stress
and quite honestly a lot of them will
develop psychological issues but you
keep on going because you f you think
that if I fall behind I'm dead. Okay, so
that is the first major issue. But now
what Donnie is going to do is he's also
going to bring another issue which is
homosexuality.
Okay,
And this is really confusing for us,
right? Because we've all seen Brock
Mountain. Brock Mountain, right? We all
know that for the longest time
homosexuals were persecuted in society.
They had to hide. They their love was
forbidden. So, isn't being a homosexual
an act of faith, hope, and love? What
does DA have against homosexuals? And
you can't be like, well, he's just a
part of his times. Because, as we said
in this class, we have to assume that
Donn is perfect and that he is timeless.
Okay? So, what what we need to figure
out is what is the problem with
homosexuality? And also, we need to be
careful because um if I say anything bad
about homosexuality, I'm pretty sure
next time I'm I'm at Yale, I'll get
stoned to death. Yeah. So, yes. Yes. You
think I'm exaggerating, but I'm not.
Yes.
>> So, I actually had this conversation
with my husband about this because I
have a lot of gay friends. I think
they're the best in the world. And he's
like, "Yeah, but there are problems with
homosexuality." So, we had this debate.
So, if anything I say, it's my husband.
Okay? Don't blame me. Don't stall me.
But he said that the actual problem with
it is kind of the same as greed and all
that other things is that after you go
through with all these acts or love or
whatever, it brings to no futation of um
because what essentially sex is at least
the way God intended for Adam and Eve is
that you are supposed to be fruitful and
multiply and occupy the earth. But if
you you are gay or homosexual, then you
essentially cannot unless you adopt a
kid, right? uh like in modern family uh
but then he's saying then you go through
all this act and love and you you don't
appreciate the other gender which is a
pers different perspective. So if you
are gay you like you are man you like
the other men then you don't actually
understand the women's perspective in
the world. So in that way you are in
love with your own kind. You're in love
with men's perspective and then that
way.
>> Okay that's great. That's brilliant.
Thank you so much for sharing that. But
let me ask you this question. Okay. It
sounds the way your husband has defined
homosexuality. It sounds like
um homosexuality sodomy belongs in the
upper circles like lust and gluttony and
wrath because you're not hurting anyone.
All you're doing is you are not
fulfilling your true potential as a
human being. But in this circle which is
a circle of violence, right? The circle
of violence. You're hurt. You actually
have to hurt someone, right? So the
question then is like how does
homosexually actually go about hurting
other people?
>> Uh yes.
>> Well, it hurts women because it denies
femininity in the world in in on earth
because
>> like all all the girls in this class are
looking at you like what are you talking
about?
>> Well [laughter] well because well
because it's normal
normal.
>> Yeah. in the Christian view
>> maybe because you know if men fall in
for love is men there's no result
because there's no no children
>> the problem with that argument is you're
saying that essentially the only purpose
of a relationship is reproduction
>> yeah exactly okay yeah Jay and then
Edward
>> in Dante's time was there a lot of
grooming going on like did he I'm just
wondering from Dante's perspective what
did he see that that made him structure
it this way
>> exactly okay so there must be something
about Dante's understanding of
homosexuality that made him resent it.
Okay. Exactly. And he'll tell us in the
next two cont. Uh this is so important
to him. He he'll spend the next two on
it. Uh yes. [clears throat] Maybe
through the historical lens when it's a
man and a woman do it, there's kind of
like the ying and yang go together.
Whereas when it's two men that
uh the act is probably more graphic and
more violent because you have two
masculine energies,
>> right?
Um okay.
Yeah. So yes,
>> I wonder if it has to do with elite
circles where they think two men are
superior to women so they refuse to. So
it's kind of almost the same as ego or
arrogance that women are inferior. So
it's making Eve kind of um the sinful,
the corrupt, weak.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Very good point. Uh because we see
in Paradigio that the upper echelons of
heaven were fully occupied by these
women and now we're getting into kind of
like the depths of hell and then we're
seeing
things.
>> Um um think about all these gay men that
you've met in your life. What what are
they obsessed about?
>> Uh yes.
>> Maybe because soulmate because uh if men
ask more about
>> like gay men in their like what what are
they obsessed about? Yeah. Yes.
>> Could be pride.
>> Excuse me.
>> Pride. Like
>> what do you mean by pride?
>> Like they they want to show they're part
of this tribe and they want to like
they're proud of it.
>> Okay. They're proud of being homosexual.
Okay. Uh no. Sorry. Sorry. Let's go by
one. Yes.
>> Sex.
They they want to have a lot of sex.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. But but what do they do every day?
Uh yes,
>> I'd say they're they would be obsessed
about finding other gay men,
>> maybe.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> Yeah. Because it's difficult to
>> No, it's not. It's not to have sex.
Okay. You're gay man.
>> Not in today today's world, but back
then probably.
>> Uh not back then either. Okay. It was
actually pretty simple.
>> Appearance.
>> Yeah. Yeah. If you meet a lot if you
meet gay men, okay, the thing about them
is like they're really obsessed with
their parents much more so than women,
right? I mean, is is that a general
statement?
>> Have a joke that if you find a guy
extremely hot and sexy, chances are he's
gay because they they care about
appearance more than straight men.
>> And and and so this is like the same
argument. Is he gay or is he just
European? like like caring about caring
about your appearance is not something
that you can just define as inherently
gay. I don't think there's a logical
correlation between that.
>> If you care too much about your parents
and all you care about your your
appearance, what word would we have to
describe you?
>> Narcissist.
>> Yeah. Narcissist. You understand?
Remember narcissist?
>> Narcissist, right? the Greek legend of
this man so in love with himself he
looks at himself every single day. Okay,
that gives us a clue as to what D's
issue of homosexuality is. You're just
looking at yourself every single day.
And so like when you actually meet
someone
like what are you looking for in that
person
yourself, right? Okay. So So that's
Donny's problem. Okay. But but but if
that's by itself, then the question then
is why is he in the circle of violence?
Because you're not actually hurting
anyone. You're just you're just like
being narcissistic, right?
Okay. All right. No, no. I Okay. Like
like like that's a question we want to
answer. Okay. But but yeah. Um Okay.
Let's keep on reading. Um,
countto 15 line 34.
>> I I I think we're where 31.
>> Oh, 31.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> So, so this is sir sir Brunetto who is
the um teacher and father figure to
Dante. And again he is in the circle of
violence because of his violence against
God. He's a homosexuality. He's a
homosexual
which goes against God in nature. Okay.
>> Verse 31. And he, my son, do not mind if
Brunetto Latino lingers for a while with
you and lets the file he's with pass on
ahead. I said, with all my strength, I
pray you stay. And if you've have you'd
have me rest a while with you, I shall
that please him with whom I go. Oh son,
he said, whoever of this flock stops but
a moment, stays a hundred years and
cannot shield himself when fire strikes.
Therefore, move on below but close, I'll
follow, and then I shall rejoin company
who go lamenting their eternal sorrows.
I do not dare to leave my path for his
own level, but I walked with head bent
low, as does a man who goes in
reverence. And he began, "What destiny
or chance has led you here below before
your last day came? And who is he who
shows the way? There, and the sunlit
life above, I answered. Before my years
were full, I went astray within a
valley. Only yesterday at dawn, I turned
my back upon it. But when I was nearly
lost, he here appeared to guide me home
again along this path. And he to me, if
you pursue your star, you cannot fail to
reach a splendid harbor. If in fair life
I judged you properly, and if I had not
died too soon for this on seeing heaven
was so kind to you, I should have helped
sustain you and your work. But that
malicious that ungrateful people come
down in ancient times from Fiesta, still
keeping something of the rock and
mountain.
For your good deeds will be your enemy,
and there is cause among the sour sorbs.
The sweet fake is not meant to bear its
fruit. The world has long since called
them blind, a people presumptuous,
aiticious, envious. Be sure to cleanse
yourself of their foul ways. Your
fortune holds in store such honor for
you, one party, and the other will be
hungry for you. But keep the grass far
from the goat. For let the beasts of
fias find forge amongst themselves, and
leave the plant alone, if still among
their dung it rises up, in which there
lives again the sacred seed of those few
Romans who remain in Florence when such
a nest of wickedness was built.
>> Okay, so this is a this is a direct
reference to the Iniad where Inias
visits his father in the underworld to
receive his prophecy and this mirrors
that. Okay. So again, this is
highlighting the fact that Subnetto
really is a father figure to um Dante.
Okay. Keep on going.
>> If my desire were answered totally, I
said to Saraponto, "You'd still be
among, not banished from humanity.
Within my memory fa is fixed and now
moves me, your dear, your kind, paternal
image, when in the world above, from
time to time you taught me how man makes
himself eternal. And while I lift, my
gratitude for that must always be
apparent in my words.
>> Okay, so he's being very explicit here,
right? You're my father. You're my
teacher. Everything I know is because of
you, right? And he's saying that if I
could, I would have you still among us.
But he can because he wrote this thing.
Okay? So this is a huge paradox for us.
Keep on going.
>> Line 88.
What do you have told me of my course? I
write. I keep it with another text for
comment by one who understand if I may
reach her. One thing alone I'd have you
plainly see, so long as I am not rebuked
by conscience, I stand prepared for
fortune come what may. My years find no
new pledge in that prediction.
Therefore, let fortune turn her wheel as
she may please and let the peasant turn
his medic. At this my master turned his
head around and toward the right and
looked at me and said, "He who takes
note of this has listened well. But
nonetheless, my talk with Sarah Brunetto
continues. And I ask of him who are his
comrades of repute and excellence. And
he to me to know of some is good, but
for the rest silence is to be praised.
The time we have is short for so much
talk. In brief know that my company has
clerics and men of letters and of fame,
and all were stained by one same sin
upon the earth.
>> Okay. All right. Okay. Okay. So this is
again very problematic in that he's
saying that with me are men who are
clerics and men who are poets and men
who are extremely successful. Okay. So
this is a huge problem because
regardless of your achievements
you're still stuck here just because you
happen to like other men.
All right. This is this is very
paradoxical. It is very It is very It is
It is not something that we've ever seen
from Dante before. Okay. This doesn't
not make any sense on the surface. Keep
on going.
>> No. That sorry crowdo holds Precinian
and Franchesco Dorso and among them you
can see if you have any longing for such
scarf.
the one the servant of his servant sent
from the Arno to the B bakigle's banks
and there he left his tendon strained by
sin I would say more but both my walk
and words must not be longer for beyond
I see new spoke emerging from the sandy
bed now people come with whom I must not
be let my toorrow in which I so live be
precious to you and I ask no more and
then he turned and seemed like one of
those who race across the fields to win
the green cloth at Verona. Of those
runners, he appeared to be the winner,
not the loser.
>> Okay. All right. So, uh, in next count,
counter 16, we will meet three really
distinguished Florentines. Okay. These
are aristocrats and they're extremely
virtuous. And back in Florence, everyone
praises them. Uh, but again, just
because of their homosexuality, they're
condemned to the circle of violence.
Okay. Uh, let's read
>> KTO 16.
No sooner had I reached the place where
one could hear a murmur like a beehive's
hum of waters as they fell to the next
circle when setting out together three
shades ran leaving another company that
passed beneath the rain of bitter
punishment. They came toward us and each
of them cried out, "Stop you who by your
clothing seem to be someone who comes
from our indecent country. A me what
once I saw upon their limbs once new and
old once that the flame seared in. It
pains me still as I remember it. When
they cried out, my master paid
attention. He turned his face toward me,
and then he said, "Now wait. To these
one must to these one must show
courtesy. And were it not the nature of
this place for shafts of fire to fall,
I'd say that haste was seem for you than
for those three." As soon as we stood
still, they started up their ancient
whale again. And when they reached us,
they formed a wheel, three of them
together. As champions, naked, oiled,
will always do. Each studying the grip
that serves him best before the blows
and wounds begin to fall. While
wheeling, so each one made sure his face
was turned to me so that their necks
opposed their feet in one uninterrupted
flow.
>> Okay, so these three individuals are the
three most distinguished members of the
Florentine nobility. Okay, they're so
distinguished that even Virgil admires
and respects them.
Okay. Uh
>> line 28.
And if the squalor of this shifting sand
together with our baked and barren
features makes us in our request
contemptable, one said, "Then may our
fume incline, may our fame incline our
mind to tell us who you are, whose
living feet can make their way through
hell with such assurance. He in whose
steps you see me tread although he now
must wheel about both peeled and naked
was higher in degree than you believe.
He was a grandson of the good guardrada
and guida was his name in life his sword
and his good sense accomplished much the
other who behind me trample sand. Tagayo
Albrandi, one whose voice should have
been heeded in the world above. And I
who share this punishment
with them was Yakapo Rustikuchi.
Certainly more than all else. My savage
wife destroyed me. If I'd had shield and
shelter from the fire, I should have
thrown myself down there among them. I
think my master would have sanctioned
that. But since that would have left me
burned and baked, my fear went out
against the good intention that made me
so impatient to embrace them. Then I
began. Your present state had fixed not
scorn but sorrow in me and so deeply
that it will only disappear slowly. As
soon as my lord spoke to me with words
that made me understand what kind of men
were coming toward us, men of worth like
yours. For I am your city. and with
fondness I've always told and heard the
others tell of both your actions and
your honored names. I leave the gall and
go for the sweet apples that I was
promised by my truthful guide. But first
I must ascended to the center.
So may your soul long lead your limbs
and may your fame shine after you. He
answered then tell us if courtesy and
valor still abide within our city as
they did when we were there. Or have
they disappeared completely? For
Guielier,
who only recently has come to share our
torments and goes there with our
companions, has caused us much
affliction with his words.
Newcomers to the city and quick gains
have brought excess and arrogance to
your floor and say you weep for it
already. So I cried out.
>> Wait, wait. So, so the words excess and
arrogance. Okay. Access and arrogance
also. Um, excess and arrogance.
These are
this is the current state of
Florence. Okay. Access and arrogance.
Okay. Keep on going.
76.
So I cried out with face up race. The
three looked at each other when they
heard my answer. As men will stare when
they have heard the truth. If you can
always offer reply so readily to others,
said all three, then happy you who speak
at will so clearly. So if you can escape
these lands of darkness and see the
lovely stars on your return when you
repeat with pleasure I was there. Be
sure that you remember us to men. At
this they broke their wheel and as they
fled their swift legs seemed to be no
less than wings. The time it took for
them to disappear more brief than time
it takes to say amen. And so my master
thought it right to leave. I followed
him. We'd only walked a little. When
roaring water grew so near to us, we
hardly could have heard each other
speak. And even as the river that is
first to take its own course eastward
from Mount Viso along the left flank of
the Epanines, which up above is called
the Aquacetta before it spills into its
valley bed and flows without that name
beyond for reverberates above Sunbed
Benedetto Dalpe
as it cascades in one leap where there
is space enough to house a thousand. So
did we hear that blackened water roar as
it plunged down a steep and craggy bank
enough to deafen us in a few hours.
Around my waist I had a cordis girdle
and with it once I thought I should be
able to catch the leopard with the
painted hide. And after I had loosened
it completely just as my guide commanded
me to do I handed it to him nodded and
coiled. At this he wheeled around upon
his right and cast it at some distance
from the edge, straight down into the
depth of the ravine. And surely
something strange must hear reply, I
said within myself, to this strange
sign, the sign my master follows with
his eye, "Ah, how much care men ought to
exercise with those whose penetrating
intellect can see our thoughts, not just
our outer act." He said to me, "Now
there will soon emerge what I await and
what your thought has conjured. It soon
must be discovered to your sight." Faced
with that truth which seems a lie, a man
should always close his lips as soon as
he can. To tell it shames him, even
though he's blameless, but here I can't
be still. And by the lines of this my
comedy reader, I swear. And may my verse
find favor for long years.
That through the dense and darkened air,
I saw a figure swimming, rising up
enough to bring amazement to the firmst
heart, like one returning from the
waves, where he went down to loose an
anchor snagged upon a reef or something
else hid in the sea, who stretches
upward and jaws in his feet.
>> Okay, so uh now they will descend down
to the circle of fraud. Now, okay, so
let's think about this. Um, Sir Bernetto
was in Alaskanto and this creates a
paradox, right? Why would Dante put
um such a man he loves in the circle of
violence and that creates a paradox. But
now in this KTO the paradox is the
paradox strengthens because these three
individuals are the best Florence has to
offer. Okay, they are the best of the
nobility and they are also suffer with
Sir Bernat. So clearly Dante wants us to
think about what's going on here. Okay,
why are these four individuals
who commit no other sin other than
homosexuality?
Why are they in uh the circle of
violence? And in the worst in the worst
part, right, because they they have
committed violence against God. All
right. Yes.
It could be seen as
>> Yeah, go ahead. It's fine. Go ahead.
>> I think it could be seen as violence
because it could lead to the end of
humanity. And um I'm thinking this
because if we're a reflection of the
universe and if we engage in
homosexuality, that would mean the
universe could engage in that. And if we
tended to the end of times, then it's
the end of humanity.
>> Okay. Yeah. Sure. That is the
explanation that's offered, right? But
again, does that make sense to you?
It has to make sense, right? Yes.
>> Yeah. Uh actually, uh I don't think it
makes sense. I'm not gay, of course, but
uh you know, I still believe that if you
have free will and you have love and why
you can't just be a homosexual. I mean,
>> yeah. So, so again, it's a problem for
us, right? If why why is homosexuality
so bad? Okay. All right. So, let's
figure this out. And again to read
Dante, you have to weed with your
imagination, right? You have to use your
imagination. So let's use imagine
imagine and ask ourselves if we were
designing
this circle, right? Violence against
God,
who would we put in the circle? What is
the worst thing in life you can do
um and which would offend both God and
nature? What is it?
No, that's violence against yourself,
right? There are already three crimes.
Violence against others, violence
against yourself, and the violence
against God and nature. I'm saying like
what is probably the most unnatural act
we could ever do?
>> Incest.
>> Exactly.
Incest, guys. Do you understand? There
could be bestiality having sex with
animals, but that's not as bad as having
sex with your sister. Okay, do you
understand this? Let me ask you this
question. Besides homosexuality, what
else is pretty common among the elite?
>> Incest.
>> Incest is pretty common among the elite,
right? Because they want to maintain a
bloodline. Because they want to maintain
a purity. Do you understand?
Okay. So this is implicit here. If it is
violence against God in nature,
people commits incest have to be here in
have to be here as well. But they're not
mentioned which forces us to imagine
they're here. Okay. Now let's think
about this. Okay. Um let us use our
imagination figure out what is
connection between homos homosexuality
and incest.
What is it? What's the problem?
What is the connection? Yes.
>> In sex is having sex with your own kind.
And so is homosexuality with your own
kind like your own gender,
>> right? And so what are you doing in
society?
>> What do you do with other people?
>> You exclude.
>> Exclusion. You understand? It's
exclusion.
The purpose of this is to exclude other
people. The elite only want to um
maintain their privileges and and block
social mobility. Okay, this the violence
against God and nature.
Okay,
social mobility.
Um okay,
and openness, right?
Homosexuality. It's the expression of
self-love
and self-indulgence.
It's the expression of excess and
arrogance. Right? We are so superior to
you. We'll only have sex with our kind
and of ourselves. We refuse to associate
with any of you. Right? And then over
time what happens
if the elite engage in homosexuality and
incest what happens now
>> extinction because with incest your
weaker gene gets combined and you have a
lot of um
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Yes. Exactly. Okay. So this threat
Yes.
>> Um I'm just just push I just just uh
kind of deducing just pushing this logic
further. So yes, if the elite only
engages in homosexuality, then um they
don't reproduce. They get to appoint you
know who they who will inherit their
power, their wealth and then so on and
so forth. So so it's a much more kind of
um controlled way of propagating power,
wealth
and all that.
>> Oh yes. Right. Okay. All right. So let
me now now let's do compare and
contrast. Okay. Let's think about a
society
in which the elite
don't practice homosexuality
and let's think about a society in which
they do practice homosexuality.
Okay. All right. So I mean again
we can generalize and say that as
society rises okay there is less homos
homosexuality and as society declines
there is more homosexuality.
Does that make sense?
Right? As if a society is poor, there's
less likely to be homosexuality. If
society is rich and declining, there's
more likely to be homosexuality.
All right?
And the example of this is now just
western culture. If you just turn on TV,
homosexuals are not persecuted, right?
They are celebrated,
right? before um you know in America you
had you had a gay politician Peter
Buddhaj before it would it would blow
the imagination that any politician
would be like would say I'm gay I'm
proud of it and please vote for me right
it it blow the imagination now but but
you know in 2020 when Pet just ran for
the um Democrat nomination his
homosexuality made him very popular
all right so my question to you is
what's the difference? What's the
difference between a society where
homosexuality is persecuted and a
society which celebrates homosexuality?
>> Uh yes, you first.
>> Um because before uh homosexuality meant
exclusion whereas now I think it's more
way more inclusion where we see as
they're way more open-minded and they're
open to engage in any culture,
philosophy.
>> Yeah, but that's a good thing, right?
But I'm asking you why Donn would think
this this represents a society in
decline.
>> Oh,
>> right. Because he clearly lamenting
about Florence, right? He's clearly he
says that Florence right now is a city
of excess and arrogance, right? And
homosexuality is a very important part
of that. So, I'm trying to figure out
why that's the case. Why is it that you
embrace homosexuality, it makes society
much more open, but it causes you to
decline?
That's a paradox, right? But it is
historically true
with the fall of Rome. Yes. I I think
sorry I think at the time it didn't make
your society more opened. I think it's
only applicable today where so before it
was exclusion whereas now the whole
aspect of it changed. So I think
>> could you could you repeat that? I'm not
sure I understood you. I think at the
time of Dante uh homosexuality was uh
about exclusion. So it was uh more of a
negative aspect whereas today it's more
about open-minded. And so before it
wasn't about openness, it was
>> So you think homosexuality is a good
thing.
>> It's good for society.
>> I'm saying it it changed. So before it
was like um against open-mindedness and
now it's more open. Right. So, so, so
I'm I'm just asking you a question which
is like
>> what D is saying is that homosexuality
is a sign of social decline. There's
lots of homosexuality today everywhere
in China and United States. Is it a good
thing or bad thing? Do you think?
>> But I I just think the definition
changed. So, if you think it's a bad
thing and this this thing changed, then
it like you can't just say it's a bad
thing today. You know, the definition
>> the definition of homosexual has not
changed, right? It's still sex between
two guys. How's that changed? Uh, so
yeah, go ahead.
>> So, yeah, I think I understand his
question that he thinks that
homosexuality today represents openness
instead of closeness and exclusiveness.
Uh, so then it shall be elevated because
it's a good thing to embrace. But I will
argue that if we look at the France
Olympics in a few past few years um the
so homosexuality or like the elevation
of this and transgender and everything
as well uh that it actually deprivives
of women or the other sex more because
what happens with the French uh Olympics
the other year that's why JK Rowling got
into this huge thing too uh is that the
man boxer who changed to be women and
then he beat up all the female male
competitor. So, no one won the box. The
female uh female champion for boxing was
a man basically. So, it excludes and
actually, you know, deny the the actual
the natural
>> I understand, but I'm still trying to
figure out why homosexuality would cause
society to decline. Yes.
>> Could it be that when societies arising,
there's like a natural order and a
natural law that everyone follows? But
when the society is falling, it's like I
can't remember who it was, but I
remember hearing someone once say that
like homosexuality is the ultimate act
of contrarianism. And it's like when you
start rejecting all of the sort of
natural laws. So it's not really just
about the homosexuality. It's that if
you adopt this mindset where there is no
natural law, it will extend into
basically the breakdown of morality. But
so so why is there this breakdown of
natural law? Why do people not follow
natural law? Uh
yeah, go ahead.
>> Um actually I don't think homosexuality
means that they're embracing everything
and openness. I think it's actually
means um
the opposite. There's a book called the
closing of American ma mind uh which is
basically saying uh if you o open and
like embrace every culture uh in the end
you're not not you you're actually um
like exclusion
>> okay yes I would like to say from Dan's
perspective he regards like the
homosexual is a bad thing for the
society I say maybe uh it's I the uh
homosexuality obey the law that god gave
us. So like for example initially when
the ward has been created why we have
two genders like male and female that
means there is naturally that there
should be attraction between male and
female to make sure we can alive and um
this the civilization could be continued
right so if people are homosexual they
are kind of prevent this natural law
that given by the god to proceed you
know
>> okay let me answer this question okay
let me answer this question
homosexuality today is celebrated.
Homosexuality before was persecuted. Did
the percentage of homosexuals
homosexuals in society did it go up or
down?
>> Down up
>> I think it's pretty similar. Okay. Do
you understand? There were lots of
homosexualities before. It's Yes.
>> So I have a I have a few comments. First
of all, I think uh metaph metaphorically
homosexuality can be described as
violence against love.
It's physical uh in the sense that um
it's uh not celestial, it's not
emotional, but it's uh it's physical.
That that's why and we need not only
celestial love, but also fleshly love.
And that's um that's a divine order. And
in that sense uh homosexual
homosexuality is a rejection
of the uh female appeal and also the
order of love on the on the flesh on the
on the physical level. Uh but I agree
with some of the comments that said um
[clears throat]
uh homosexuality is uh is as bad as is
as bad as incest in ex in causing more
inclus exclusion because
uh from the genetic point of view
although I do have some reservation uh
about genetics uh from genetic point of
view homosexual attitude actually
results in the uh in the uh in the
distrib distribution of the wealth from
the elite more to the for the people who
can procreate.
>> And if the elite choose not to uh engage
in uh you know bisexual uh sex then it
will cause more you know fair
distribution. Whereas incest is a is an
attempt for the elite to create uh you
to concentrate the wealth in uh in more
homogeneous gene which is bad for
society.
Okay. All right. So, let me ask you this
question. Okay. How does Donn feel about
the elite?
What does he think about the elite? This
nobility? How how does he perceive the
nobility? Do you think
>> entitled?
>> Yeah, they're entitled. Are they a good
thing or a bad thing? Of
>> of of course they're bad.
>> They're a bad thing. So So what is So
what do you do with them? Get rid of
them?
>> What would you do? You you try to make
them humble again like
>> you make but like how do you make them
humble?
>> Okay. Okay guys like like like like I I
I don't want to spend too much time on
this. Okay. So let's film this. Okay.
First of all, how does starting feel
about no nobility?
Uh and then the question then is I want
to focus on is why is it when societies
on the rise there's less homosexuality
but when societies are in the are in
decline there's more homosexuality when
I mean what I mean by I mean like like
there's more open outward homosexuality
right the percentage probably say the
same right but societies are on the rise
the elite they would not practice their
homosexuality in open right they hide it
they they would hide did they would
still get married and have children. Now
they're just practicing out in the open.
What's the difference? Uh yes, you you
then you
>> uh I think there's two things. First,
it's about needs. Once you have like
everything you need, then you try to
seek something else. So when a society
has access to food, protection and etc.
You try to engage in something new that
could be homosexuality.
And also it could be due to a dating
aspect because it's if a society is very
well constructed and becomes very
competitive then you have a really low
chance to access to the 1% 5% above and
so you just engage in your own gender.
>> Okay. Yes. You
>> Yeah. I I agree and I think it just
refers to the aspect of hope in a
declining society. If you like don't
have kids as a homosexual, then you say
that you don't have hope in the future.
>> Okay. Okay. All right. For the future.
>> So, so, so, so I I want to change the
question. Okay.
>> Okay. Imagine you're at Yale. Okay.
You're a freshman at Yale. Okay.
And you know the answer. So, so, so you
and I won't participate. Okay. But
imagine you're at Yale or Harvard or
Princeton. And in 1960s, you go into
Yale and the president is addressing
you, right?
What is going to say to you? You're
saying you're at Yale to do what in
1960s or 70s or 80s or 90s.
Exactly. Right. Change the world. Better
humanity.
Service humanity. Right.
Today when you're at Yale, Harvard, or
Princeton, the president says what to
you? If you're at university, you know
the answer. What's the answer?
Be yourself.
It be yourself. Your identity is what
matters.
Right? Am I wrong here?
Be yourself. Celebrate yourself.
That's why society declines. Do you
understand?
That's from the elite. That's why
homosexuality is a problem because it's
not the act itself. It's the attitude.
Be yourself. Indulge yourself. Love
yourself.
Don't worry about other people. Don't
worry about your responsibility to
society. Don't try to change the world
for better. Just celebrate yourself and
be happy.
And if you're And if you're not happy,
complain about it.
Celebrate yourself. Am I wrong? It
Okay. Okay. That's what Don is saying
here. He's saying that homosexuality
like incest, it represents a like an
inward turning, right? A narcissism that
is extreme. So, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Go
ahead. Yes.
>> So, does he say that it's not real love?
>> No. No. You You can't love yourself
other men.
>> Well, no. But but like what he's saying
is like when you love other men, what
you're really doing is loving yourself.
It's a narcissism, right? Because
narcissist saw himself in the mirror.
Um and he wanted to like have sex with
him himself. That's what homosexuality
is. It's narcissist having sex w with
with himself. And I'm not saying that's
right. I'm just saying like like this is
how Dante perceives this. Okay.
All right.
Yes.
Why is Dante neglecting the narcissist
aspect in heterosexuality? Because like
as we see today, there are people who
focus on looks to attract women. Um and
so just pointing out the narcissistic
narcissistic aspect in homosexuality
would be neglecting the this aspect in
the other side,
>> right? Yes. Okay. That's a really
interesting question. Um, and
unfortunately in hell we don't have
narcissism as a sin. Why not?
Okay, the answer is um at this time in
history, what Dante is trying to do is
he's trying to he's trying to change
um the idea of the ego, right? So, um
the Catholic Church is teaches teaches
you that ego is bad. Self self- loveve
does is the worst sin the worst evil.
Right? And what Don is saying is that if
that's your attitude, you can't actually
go and change the world for the better.
You have to believe that you are so
good, God loves you so much that you
will have the power to change the world
for the better. Okay? And um and that's
why the three um sins
um sorry, there are two sins, envy and
pride, he actually doesn't list in
infernal. He will list them in purgatory
but not infernal. Okay. So, so, so that,
so that's what Donnie is trying to do.
He he's trying to tell us that self-love
is a good thing, but self- loveve as
expressed with other men is a bad thing.
Okay? Because it's self-indulgent.
Okay? So, homosexuality by itself is not
bad. The act isn't bad, but the attitude
of it is bad, which is like like all I
care about is myself. I'm loving myself.
I'm celebrating myself. That's the
issue. Okay? Does that make sense? All
right. All right. So, um I make this
comment, right? And so what Don is
saying is that nobility is not good or
bad. It's how the nobility behaves
that's good or bad, right? Nobility is
behaving towards betterment of society
that they're good. But if they are
behaving like narcissists, that's bad.
Okay, that can only mean the destruction
of society because at this point in
history, it is not possible to imagine a
society without the nobility, right?
It's you can't have communism. No one's
going to imagine communism at this
point. And think about how how unfair
that would be, right? This family has
spent generations um putting all this
wealth and you just take it from them.
They so so D would never suggest that.
What he what he's what he's suggesting
is that nobility have a distinct
responsibility to the rest of society to
contribute. Okay? And when they engage
in homosexuality, it just shows that
they have abandoned society. Okay? They
don't even care about hypocrisy anymore.
they can't even bother to uh demonstrate
propriety
and um uh leadership to everyone else.
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, so to
confirm that what I'm saying is correct,
what we're going to do is we're going to
read Paradiso 16. Okay, so Dante has an
amazing way of mirroring himself,
creating symmetry. So we are in we were
inferno 16. We're now going to jump to
Paradisel 16 where um Dante is going to
talk to his great-grandfather and his
great-grandfather is going to share the
story of his family and the story of
Florence. Okay. So this is the early
days of Florence when the elite working
hard to build a greater Florence and you
can compare contrast these two contos.
Okay. So so so let's read Paradosa 16.
Paradiso Conto 16.
If here below, where sentiment is far,
too weak to withstand error, I should
see men glorying in you, nobility of
blood, a meager thing, I should not
wonder, for even where desire is not
arry, I mean in heaven I too felt such
pride. You're indeed a cloak that soon
wears out, so that if day by day we add
no patch, then circling time will trim
you with its shears. My speech began
again with you. The word that Rome was
the first city to allow, although her
people seldom speak it now. At this
word, Beatatrice, somewhat apart,
smiling, seemed like the woman who had
coughed. So goes the tale at Guyavir's
first fault. So did my speech begin.
You're my father. You hearten me to
speak with confidence. You raised me so
that I am more than I. So many streams
have filled my mind with gladness. So
many and such gladness that mine must
rejoice that it can bear this and not
burst. Then tell me, founder of my
family, who were your ancestors, and in
your boyhood, what were the years of
records registered? And tell me of the
sheepfold of St. John, how numerous it
was, who in that flock were worthy of
the highest offices. As at the breathing
of the winds, a coal will quicken into
flame. So I saw that light glow at words
that were affectionate. And as before,
my eyes it grew more fair, so with a
voice more gentle and more sweet, not in
our modern speech it said to me. Down
from that day, when a was pronounced,
until my mother, blessed now, by giving
birth, eased the burden born and bearing
me, this fire of Mars had come 550 and
30 more times to its lion, there to be
rekindled underneath its paw.
My ancestors and I were born just were
where the runner in your early games
hers comes upon the boundary of the
final ward. That is enough concerning my
forebears. What were their names from
where they came of that silence not
speech is more appropriate? All those
who at that time between the Baptist and
Mars were capable of bearing arms
numbered one of those who live there
now. But then the citizens now mixed
with compi, with the chhatalo, and with
the fig f figi were pure down to the
humblest artisan. Oh, it would be far
better if you had those whom I mention
as your neighbors and your boundaries at
Galudo and Trespiano than to have them
within to bear the stench of Agulion
rich and saas whose sharp eyes now are
embarrass
if those who in the world go most astray
had not seen Caesar with stepmother's
eyes but like a mother to her son been
kind the one who has become a Florentine
trader and money changer would have
stayed in semifonte
where his father's pedal
the counts would still be lords of Monty
Murlo the Cherokee would be in Aone's
parish perhaps the buantee in Vadere the
mingling of the populations led to evil
in the city even as food piled on food
destroys the body's health the blind
bull falls more quickly more headlong
than does the blind lamb and the one
blade can often cut more and better than
five swords Consider
Looney Obisalia, how they went to ruin,
ruin, sin Galileia follows, and Cusi too
will soon have vanished. Then if you
should hear of families undone, you will
find nothing strange or difficult in
that. Since even cities meet their end,
all things that you possess possess
their death, just as you do. But in some
things that last long, death can hide
from you whose life are short. And even
as the heaven of the moon revolving
respitless conceals and then reveals the
shores, so fortune does with Florence.
Therefore there's no cause for wonder in
what I shall tell of noble Florentines
of those whose reputations time has
hidden. I saw the Ugi, saw the Catalini,
Filipe, Gretchi, Ormani of Alberiki,
fame citizens already in decline, and
saw as great as they were venerable,
Delarka with Delisanella, and Aringi,
Sodanari, and Bastiki.
Nearby the gate that now is burdened
with new treachery that weighs so
heavily that it will bring the vessel to
shipwreck. There were the Ravenani from
whose line Count Buido comes. And all
who since derived their name from the
illustrious Bellachion,
and Delressa knew already how to rule,
and Galayo in his house already had the
gilded hilt and palmold. The stripe of
Vier had mightiness already, as did the
Joki, Gali, and Baruchi Fontin,
those who blush for the bushel. And the
stock from which sprang from Kuchi was
already mighty, and Sitzi and Arguchi
were already raised to high office. Oh,
how great were those I saw, whom pride
laid low, and the gold balls in all of
her great actions flowered Florence.
Such were the ancestors of those who
now, whenever Bishop sees are vacant,
grow fat as they sit in church
consisties.
The breed so arrogant and dragonlike and
chasing him who flees, but lamblike,
meek to him who shows his teeth, or else
his purse was on the rise already, but
of stock so mean that Uberin Donato,
when his father-in-law made him kin to
them, was scarcely pleased already.
Capons can had come from Full down to
the market. Already citizens of note
were Judah and Infantato. I shall tell a
thing incredible and true. the gateway
through the inner walls were named for
the deliper.
All those whose arms bear part of the
fair and sign of the great baron. He
whose memory and worth are honored on
the feast of Thomas received knighthood
and privilege from him. Those he whose
co code coat of arms has fringed that
ensign has taken sides now with the
populace.
The Guarati and the importunity were
there already, where the Borgo spared
new neighbors, it would still be
tranquil there. The house of Amade with
which your sorrows began by reason of
its just resentment which ruined you and
ended years of gladness were honored
then as were its close companions. A
bonde through another's council. You
fled your wedding pledge and brought
such evil. Many would now rejoice who
still lament if when you first
approached the city God had given you
unto the river Emma. But Florence in her
final peace was faded to offer up unto
that mutilated stone guardian upon her
bridge a victim. These were the families
and others with them the Florence that I
saw in such repose that there was
nothing to have caused her sorrow. These
were the families. With them I saw her
people so acclaimed and just that on her
staff the lily never was reversed nor
was it made blood red by factious
hatred.
>> Okay. So um here uh Donniey's
great-grandfather
is recounting the glory of Florence and
explaining why Florence ultimately
declined. Okay. So for the
greatgrandfather,
what's the main reason why Florence
declined? If you talk to any old person,
okay, it's always this reason.
What is it? What what led to the clim of
Florence?
>> Excess and arrogance.
>> No, no, maybe maybe that's Dante. But
here it's different.
This this is the great-grandfather and
he's like this is why Florence went
down. Yes.
>> People's greed towards materials and
like money.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But but where did that come
from? Where did this materialism come
from?
>> Chase for power.
>> What caused Yes.
>> Factious hatred?
>> No. What's causing this materialism?
What's causing this hatred?
Come on. I mean, like you just talk to
your grandparents, right? And like your
grandparents are like, "Yeah, before
this was a great neighborhood, but then
what happened?
Before
this was a lovely neighborhood and
everyone got along great. But then
>> maybe something about the young people.
>> No. What happened guys?
>> Maybe people became selfish.
>> No,
someone new came into the neighborhood.
>> Immigrants.
>> Goddamn immigrants.
Okay.
again. Um, this is not a political
correct class. Okay.
Why is immigration bad?
>> Why is immigration bad?
>> It puts into conflict people with
different cultures.
>> Okay. Yes. It creates a cultural clash.
Yes. What else?
>> Because the values you hold is
different.
>> Exactly. Okay. your values change.
Before these old families were dedicated
to helping other people around them,
helping their neighbors. But when you
have people with so many values come in
like that are different from yours,
what's your only solution to this
problem of immigration?
>> Like exclude them. So you have your own
societ communities.
>> Okay. So exclusion but I'm saying how do
you unite the entire city through what?
>> To be more conservative.
>> Uh no one no the old people. Yes.
>> Assimilation maybe like
>> but how do you assimilate them?
>> Yeah. Oh your your stuff is cool too. We
accept everything like everything is
cool. We're solid.
>> So materialism
>> money.
Do you understand? If you have
immigrants come in everyone shares
different values. The only value that
you have to create to unify society is
money. Right? And money leads to the
separation of selfishness, right? That's
why you can't no longer be change the
world because that's western
imperialism. It has to be be yourself,
separate yourself. Okay? And how do you
do that? Go make a lot of money.
So this is a pattern throughout human
history. Okay? We you think that oh look
isn't it great that if you work hard you
can you can be a trillionaire. No it's
not. I mean how about contributing to
your community? How about working hard
to create families? How about
um making a
safe and moral society?
Right? But you're not taught that.
You're taught just go make a lot of
money and be yourself and celebrate
yourself. And if you want to be gay,
great. Okay. Does that make sense?
All right. So again, again, um this is
not politically correct. Okay. But but
again, we're trying to examine why
societies decline. And so you have
thought is saying you have immigrants,
you have homosexuality, you have
factionalism, you have economic
pressure.
Okay.
And are they still are they true today?
Yeah, they're very much true today. So
according to Dante, we are very much a
society in decline. Does anyone want to
argue against this?
Like I I don't want to be seen as
brainwashing you. Okay. Do you want to
argue against this?
>> Yes. Thank you. Well, with immigration,
I want to point out that for example
with World War II in the in Europe when
uh many people are persecuted, they came
to see the United States as the promised
land and where you won't be persecuted.
So um a lot of the best scientists and
intellectuals and whoever it is went to
America. So um you know immigration can
create um kind of u more vibrancy in
society.
>> Sure. Yeah. That that's a great um
argument.
>> Yes.
>> The population decline. So like you
bring people because your culture
doesn't makes enough children to finance
your society.
>> Yeah. But why is your population
declining?
>> I don't know. Yeah.
>> No, you do know why why why population
is declining. It's because
>> it's too expensive. People make less
kids.
>> Well, come on, man.
>> It's a lack of social mobility.
>> Yeah. Lack of social mobility,
homosexuality,
uh narcissism. Okay. Do you understand?
So, publish decline is a symptom of of
society decline. And immigration is just
a short-term remedy. It's not a
long-term solution. Uh yes. um
population could also decline because
the cost of raising a child is
increased.
>> Yeah, exactly. But that's also a sudden
decline, right? Where you can't even
where young people can can no longer
afford to have families. Okay. Uh yes.
>> Maybe because the people just do not
believe in God because they believe in
money and money can help themselves,
right? But
>> yeah, the lack of religion, right? Okay.
Uh okay. But but I'm saying like argue
against Dante. Okay. And what Carol says
is Yeah. But immigration allows for more
vibrancy, allows for more creativity,
right? And and also like if you don't
let an immigrant, society is going to is
going to decline even further, even
faster. Uh yes. Anyone else to argue
against this?
>> In
more developed economies, immigrant
workers are often a cheaper source of
labor.
>> But is but is that a good thing? Like,
you know, let's bring in poor people to
exploit. I mean,
>> exploit [laughter] them. I mean really
>> for the capitalists it's a good thing
>> right I'm sure it is any other arguments
against this
>> yes
>> I think it helps with unity in the world
cuz like if every culture is represented
in every country then it creates unity
and we all move together towards one
path.
>> Exactly. So you look at the World Cup,
right? Uh America right now is hosting
their World Cup. You go to every
stadium, it's packed with different
cultures and they're all celebrating uh
together, right? So multiculturalism.
Sure.
>> What else? Yes.
>> Yeah. Like multiculturalism kind of
brings you different perspectives so
that you can actually debate uh between
values. You kind of examine truth from
different lenses and perspectives. So it
gives you maybe it might get you closer
to the truth. So that's why I think the
pope actually last month met with the
the Muslim leader. So the two of them
had a talk. So it's like be more
embracing of a different religion,
culture, perspective.
>> Right. Okay. So it makes everyone much
more tolerant, right? Much more open.
That's great. Okay. So, um, that's all
great, but
how to explain to Dante the lack of
creativity in our world today?
Why is it in today's world,
no one is able to write the Divine
Comedy? I I I actually can't remember
the last good book I read or the last
good movie I saw. I literally cannot.
Yes.
for our needs and we stop suffering and
so we don't need to engage in anything
difficult also because of technology. Um
everything is simple for us and so it's
just we have nothing to talk about or no
no energy that can make us create new
stuff.
>> Okay, you're absolutely right. Yes.
>> Uh I think people right now are too
material and uh and not spiritual
enough.
>> Yeah, but why would that lead to a
decline in creativity? Right. Because in
theory, if you can make a trillion
dollars writing a divine comedy, why
don't you go write it, right?
Yes.
>> Uh people lost their love. Uh people are
hopeless and they just care about their
job, about money, but not about
spiritual thing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. People have Yes. Go ahead. I
>> I think I want to add on to that because
people are not only um too
materialistic. They are also like we
haven't been this spiritually away from
oursel from our inner world. I mean this
is the we've never been like this
because you see all the religions and
all the Buddhism all that thing dating
back in thousands years ago but now like
I don't it's a small portion of the
society who still talk about this I
think.
>> Right. Exactly. Okay. So this is really
interesting because if Don were to come
today to look at our world he'd be like
this is a lot worse than my world man.
Because regardless of how bad things
were back then at least they had roots
right? At least they had family and
community, a sense of of like each
other. Whereas today we are all
rootless,
right? We have no history. We have no
culture. We have no tradition. If you
say these things, then they'll say
you're racist or you're a bigot.
Okay. I I mean, right. Okay. So, it
makes you really think about what is
really valuable in society. Okay. So,
let's go to Kel 17, please.
Kanto 17.
Behold the beast who bears the pointed
tail, who crosses mountains, shatters
weapons walls. Behold the one whose
stench fills all the world. So did my
guide begin to speak to me. And then he
signaled him to come ashore close to the
end of those stone passageways. And he
came on that filthy effigy of fraud and
landed with his head and torsel, but did
not draw his tail unto the bank. The
face he wore was that of a just man. So
gracious was his features outer
semblance and all his trunk the body of
a serpent. He had two paws with hair up
to the armpits. His back and chest as
well as both his flanks have been
adorned with twining knots and cirlets.
No Turks or Tartars ever fashioned
fabrics more colorful in background and
relief, nor Arachnne ever loomed such
webs
as boats will sometimes lie along along
the shore with part of them on land and
part in water. And just as there among
the guzzling Germans, the beaver sets
himself when he means war, so did that
squalid beast lie on the margin of stone
that serves as bo border for the sand.
and all his tail was c quivering in the
void while twisting upward an invenimmed
fork which had a tip just like a
scorpion's. My guide said, "Now we'd
better bend our path a little till we
reach as far as that malicious beast
which crouches over there."
Thus we descended on the right hand side
and moved tense paces on the stony brink
in order to avoid the sand and fire.
When we had reached the sprawling beast,
I saw a little father on on upon the
sandsome sinners sitting near the
fissured rock. And here my master said
to me, "So that you may experience this
ring in full, go now and see the state
in which they are. But keep your
conversation with them brief, till you
return, I'll parlay with these beast to
see if he can lend us his strong
shoulders."
So I went on alone and even farther
along the seven circles outer margin to
where the melancholy people sat. The
spondency was bursting from their eyes
decide than that their hands kept
fending off at times the flames at times
the burning soil. Not otherwise do dogs
in summer now with muzzle now with paw
when they're bitten by fleas or gnats or
by the sharp gadfly. When I had set my
eyes upon the faces of some on whom that
painful fire falls, I recognized no one.
But I did notice that from the neck of
each a purse was hung that had a special
color and an emblem, and their eyes
seems to feast upon these pouches.
Looking about when I had come among
them, I saw a yellow purse with azure on
it that had the face and manner of a
lion. Then, as I let my eyes move
farther on, I saw another purse that was
blood red and displaced a goose more
whiter than butter, and one who had an
azure pregnant so inscribed as emblem on
his white pouch, said to me, "What are
you doing in this pit? Now you be off,
and since you're still alive, remember
that my neighbor
shall yet sit here upon my left hand
side." Among these Florentes, I'm Padu,
and I often hear them thunder in my
ears, shouting, "Now let the sovereign
cavalere, the one who bring the purse
with three goats, come at this." He
soothed his mouth, and then he stuck his
tongue out like an ox that licks its
nose. And I, afraid that any longer stay
might anger him who warned me to be
brief, made me back from those exhausted
souls. I found my guide, who had already
climbed upon the back of that brute
animal, and he told me, "Be strong and
daring now, for our descent is by this
kind of stairs you mounted front, I want
to be between, so that the tail can't do
you any harm."
As one who feels the cord and fever near
and shivers with his nails already blue,
the sight of shade enough to make him
shudder, so I became when I had heard
these words. But then I felt the threat
of shame which makes a servant and his
kind lord's presence brave. I settled
down on those enormous shoulders I wish
to say and yet my voice did not come as
I thought. See that you hold me tight
but he who other times another danger
sustained me just as soon as I had
mounted clasp me within his arms and
propped me up and said, "Now Gurion,
move on. Take care to keep your circles
wide, your landing slow. remember the
new weight you're carrying.
Just like a boat that starting from its
moorings moves backward backward so that
beast took off and when he felt himself
completely clear he turned his tail to
where his chest had been and having
stretched it moved it like an eel and
with his paws he gathered in the air. I
do not think that there was greater fear
in fe than when he let his res go free
for which the sky as one still sees was
scorched. Nor in poor Icaras when he
could feel his sides unwinged because
the wax was melting. His father shouting
to me that waste wrong than was in me
when all on all sides I saw that I was
in the air and everything had faded from
my sight except the beast. Slowly slowly
swimming he moves on. He wheels and he
descends, but I feel only the wind upon
my face and the wind rising.
Already on our right, I heard the
torrent resounding there beneath us
horribly, so that I stretched my neck
and looked below. Then I was more afraid
of falling off, where I saw fires, and I
heard laments at which I tremble,
crouching, and hold fast. And now I saw
what I had missed before his wheeling
and descent because great torments were
drawing closer to us on all sides. Just
as a falcon long upon the wing whose
seeing neither lure nor bird compels the
falconer to cry, "A me you fall,
desense, exhausted in a hund circles
where he had once been swift, and sets
himself embittered and enraged far from
his master." such at the bottom of the
jagged rock was Gurion when he had set
us down and once our weight was lifted
from his back he vanished like an arrow
from a bow.
>> Okay. So two points the first point is
that to descend from the circle of
violence to the circle of fraud. Okay.
Uh and and quite honestly the circle of
fraud will occupy about a third of the
divine comedy. Okay. We're kind of 17.
There's 34 contos in inferno. We're
halfway through. Uh so most of most of
the time we will actually spend in the
circle of fraud. Uh as well as the
circle of treachery. Uh what takes them
down to the circle is a beast called a
Gerion. The Gerion uh has the face of an
honest man, a very good-looking man that
you trust, but has a but it has the tail
of a scorpion. Okay? So it can sting you
at any time. So that's what fraud is.
Okay, fraud seduces you and you believe
something and then uh stings you okay
that's the first point. Uh second point
is that while Virgil is taming the
Gerion
um Dante is
uh looking around and he meets these
money lenders who are buried in the
sand. What what traps them in the ground
are these purses of money. Right? So
this is a fitting [snorts]
um punishment because in life they
trapped or they enslave others with
debt, right? With interest. So So
they're getting a taste of their own
medicine. And that that's what hell is.
Um the pain that you cause onto others,
you yourself will feel for all eternity.
Okay. All right. So let's uh any
questions before we move on? Are are we
clear? Okay. So that's circle violence.
Now we we descend to the circle of fraud
which is the majority of the divine
comedy. Okay. Uh inferno um 18
>> inferno KTO 18. There's a place in hell
called Mali Boj.
>> So Mali Boj is the name of the circle.
Okay. The circle of fraud. Uh and there
are different digits for different um
frauds. Okay. made all of stone the
color of crude iron as is the wall that
makes its way around it. Right in the
middle of this evil fil field is an
abyss, a broad and yawning pit whose
structure I shall tell in its due place.
The belt then that extends between the
pit and that hard steep wall space is
circular. Its bottom has been split into
10 valleys. Just as where moonote
surrounds a castle in order to keep
guard upon the walls, the ground they
occupy will form a pattern. So did the
valleys here form a design and as such
fortresses have bridges running right
from their thresholds toward the outer
bank. So here across the banks and
ditches ridges ran from the base of that
rock wall until the pit that cuts them
short and joins them all. This was the
pace place in which we found oursel
ourselves when Gurion had put us down.
The poet held to the left and I walked
at his back. Upon the right I saw new
misery. I saw new torches and new
torturers filling the first of Malib's
moes
along its bottom. Naked sinners moved to
our side of the middle facing us beyond
that they moved with us but more quickly
as in the year of Jubilee the Romans
confronted by great crowds contrived a
plan that let the people pass across the
bridge. For to one side went all who had
their eyes upon the castle heading
toward St. Peters and to the other those
who faced the mount both left and right
along the somber rock I saw horned
demons with enormous whips who lashed
those spirits cruy from behind. Ah how
their first strokes make those sinners
lift their heels. Indeed no sinner
waited for a second stroke to fall or
for a third. And as I moved ahead my
eyes met those of someone else. And
suddenly I said, I was not spared the
sight of him before.
And so I stayed my steps to study him.
My gentle guide had stopped together
with me and gave me leave to take a few
steps back. That scourged soul thought
that he could hide himself by lowering
his face. It helped him little, for I
said, "You who cast your eyes upon the
ground, if these your features are not
false, must be Venadiko Kachcha Namiko.
But what brings you to sauces so pecan
and he to me? I speak unwillingly, but
your plain speech that brings the memory
of the old world to me is what compels
me. For it was I who led Gisabella to do
as the marquee would have her do.
However, they retell that filthy tale.
I'm not the Bolognese who weeps here.
Indeed, this place is so crown full of
us that no so not so many tongues have
learned to say seepa between the savvena
reno. If you want faith and testament of
that just call to mind our aphericious
hearts and as he spoke a demon cudgled
him with his horse whoop and cried be
off you pimp. There are no women here
for you to trick. I joined
>> okay so so these are pimps right? These
are people who sold their sisters or
others to wealthy men and Venitico is
one of them. And for their punishment,
they're being whipped around by demons.
Okay? Which is what they did in real
life to their sisters or to their
daughters or they're just pimps. Okay.
Um, keep on going.
Line 67. I joined my escort once again,
and then, with but few steps, we came
upon a place where, from the bank a
rocky ridge ran out. We climbed quite
easily along that height, and turning
right upon its jagged back, we took our
leave of those eternal circlings. When
we had reached the point where that
ridge opens below to leave a passage for
the lash, my guide said, "Stay and make
sure that the sight of still more illorn
spirits strikes your eyes, for you have
not yet seen their faces since they have
been moving in our own direction."
From the old bridge we looked down at
the ranks of those approaching from the
other side. They too were driven onward
by the lash. And my good master, though
I had not asked, urged me, "Look at that
mighty one who comes and does not seem
to shed a tear of pain. How he still
keeps the image of a king, that shade of
chase is Jason, who with heart and had
deprived the men of Kulkus of their
ram."
He made a landfall on the aisle of
Lemnos after its women, bold and
pitilous, had given all their island
males to death. With polished words and
love signs he took in hips
hipily the girl whose own deception had
earlier deceived the other women and he
abandoned her alone and pregnant. Such
guilt condemns him to such punishment.
And for media too revenge is taken. With
him go those who cheated. So this is
enough for you to know of that first
valley and of the souls it clamps within
his jaws.
>> Does anyone know the story of Jason and
Medadia?
Jason and Medadia. Jason is of the
Argonauts, right? And with Medadia's
help, he is able to retrieve the golden
fleece. So, he takes Media home to
Greece. They marry together. They have
children together. But then, in order
for Jason to
um climb even higher, he marries a
princess
and betrays Media. So, what does media
do? Do you guys know the story?
Can you guys guess what what she does?
>> Did she kill her kids?
>> Yeah, she killed her kids. Yeah. It It's
I mean like Greek tragedy. It's such a
Yeah, but but she killed her two young
kids as to avenge her betrayal. Okay.
All right. So, Yeah. Okay. Giving way
>> line 100. We were already where the
narrow path reaches and intersects the
second bank and serves as shoulder for
another bridge. We heard the people
whine in the next pouch and heard them
as they snorted with their snouts. We
heard them use their palms to beat
themselves. An exhalations rising from
above stuck to the banks encrusting them
with mold and so waged war against both
eyes and nose. The bottom is so deep we
found no spot to see it from. except by
climbing up the arch until the bridge's
highest point. This was the place we
reached. The ditch beneath held people
plunged in excrement that seemed as if
it had been poured from human privies.
And while my eyes searched that abysmal
sight, I saw one with a head so smeared
with I could not see if he were
lay or cleric.
>> Okay. So, so let's Okay. What do you do
in real life that will warrant you
uh basically
a wash in for all eternity? You're
just basically swimming in
drowning in for all eternity. What
did you do in in life? What was your
problem? Anyone?
We have the punishment, right? Which is
you just, you know, swimming
You're
what what what did you do in real in
real life?
to warrant this
>> like like on other people
like like like put other people in like
such a situation. So
>> no I mean sure um right?
>> Oh yeah.
>> Yeah. Right. Flattery Yes.
You're just BSing other people all the
time. Okay. So now you're just drowning
in it. Keep on keep on going.
>> 118. He howled. Why do you stare more
greedily at me than at the others who
are filthy and I? Because if I remember
right, I have seen you before with your
hair dry, and so I eye you more than
all. You're allesio intermina of Luca.
Then he continued, pounding on his pate.
I'm plunged here because of flatteries
of which my tongue had such sufficiency
at which my guide advised me. See you
thrust your head a little farther to the
front so that your eyes can clearly
glimpse the face of that bismerged but
draggled Herodan who scratched at
herself with shitfilled nails. And now
she crouches. Now she stands upright.
That is Tus Tus the harlot who returned
her lover's question. Are you very
grateful to me by saying yes enormously
and now our site has had its fill of
this.
>> Okay. All right. So another major
characteristic um of a siting in the
client of course is fraud, right?
Um fraud. It's just like you can't trust
each other anymore, right? Is fraud an
issue today?
>> Yeah, it's a huge issue today. Okay.
Yes. Um, did you know that 80% of all uh
cases,
criminal cases in are um internet fraud.
>> Yes. Okay. The internet, right?
>> And now we have AI. We have deep fake.
It's all It's all down.
>> Yeah. Exactly. A AI, right? So, we live
in a world of fraud. Like it's literally
now impossible to tell what is fake
news, right? It's it's really hard,
okay? And it's really hard now to trust
other people.
And so this is also a symptom of a
society in decline.
Why is this a problem?
Yes.
>> A lot of wasted energy.
>> Okay.
>> People wasting their imagination
defrauding people and people wasting
their imagination trying not to get the
get cheated.
>> Yeah. It's impossible to work together.
Do you understand? Right. It's
impossible to make promises. It's
impossible to make contracts. It's
impossible to cooperate anymore. Okay.
Um Yeah. [snorts]
Okay. Let's keep on going. K
conto 19
as Simon Maggus. Oh his sad disciples
rapacious ones who take the things of
God that ought to be the brides of
righteousness and make them fornicate
for gold and silver. The time has come
to let the trumpet sound for you. Your
place is here and in this third pouch.
We had already reached the tomb beyond
and climbed onto the ridge where its
high point hangs just above the middle
of the ditch. Oh highest wisdom, how
much art you show in heaven, earth in
this sad world below. How just your
power is when it elots along the sides
and down along the bottom. I saw that
livid rock was perforated. The openings
were all one width and round. They did
not seem to me less broad or more than
those in my handsome San Joani where
were made to serve as basins for
baptizing.
And one of these not so many not many
years ago I broke for someone who was
drowning in it. And let this be my seal
to set men straight. Out from the mouth
of each hole there emerged a sinner's
feet and so much of his legs up to the
thigh. The rest remained within. Both
souls of every sinner were on fire.
Their joints were ripening with such
violence they would have severed wives
and ropes of grass.
As flame on oily things will only stir
along the outer surface, so thereto that
fire made its way from heels to toes.
Master, I said, who's that shade who
suffers and quivers more than all his
other comrades? That sinner who's licked
by redder flames? And he to me, if you
would have me lead you down along the
steepest of the banks, from him you'll
learn about his self and sins. And I,
what pleases you will please me, too.
You are my Lord. You know I do not
swerve from what I what you will. You
know what is unspoken.
At this we came upon the fourth
embankment. We turned on keeping to the
left, ascended into the narrow,
perforated bottom. My good lord did not
let me leave his sight until he brought
me to the hole that held that sinner who
lamented with his legs. Whoever you may
be, dejected soul whose head is downward
planted like a pole. My words began, "Do
speak of your able." I stood as does the
frier who confesses the foul assassin
who fixed fast head down calls back the
frier and so delays his death. And he
cried out, "Are you already standing
already standing there, O Bonafas? The
book has lied to me by several years.
Are you so quickly sad with the riches
for which you do not fear to take by
guile the lovely lady than to violate
her?"
And I became like those who stand as if
they have been mocked, who cannot
understand what has been said to them
and can't respond. But Virgil said,
"Tell this to him at once. I'm not he
not who you think I am." and I replied
as I was told to do. At this the spirit
twisted both his feet and sighing and
with a desparing voice he said, "What is
it then you want of me?" If you have
crossed the bank and climbed so far to
find out who I am, then know that I was
one of those who wore the mighty mantle
and surely was the son of the she bear
so eager to advance the cubs that I
pursued wealth above. While here I
pursed myself.
Below my head there is the place of
those who took the way of Simony before
me. And they are stuffed within the
cliffs of stone. I too shall yield my
place and fall below when he arrives.
The one for whom I had mistaken you when
I was quick to question.
But I have baked my feet a longer time
have stood like this upon my head than
he to stand planted here with scarlet
feet. For after him one uglier in deeds
will come a lawless shepherd from the
west worthy to cover him and cover me.
He'll be a second Jason of whom we read
in Mcabes. And just as Jason's king was
soft to him, so shall the king of France
be soft to this one. And I do not know
if I was too rash here. I answered, "So
then tell me now, how much gold did our
Lord ask that St. Peter give to him
before he placed the keys within his
care? Surely the only thing he said was
follow me. And Peter and the others
never asked for gold or silver when they
chose Matias to take the place of the
transgressing soul. Stay as you are, for
you're rightly punished and guard with
care the money got by evil that made you
so audacious against Charles. And were
it not that I am still prevented by
reverence for those exalted keys that
you had held within the happy life, I'd
utter words much heavier than these.
Because your avarice afflicts the world.
It tramples on the good, lifts up the
wicked. You shepherds, the evangelist
had noticed when he saw her, who sits
upon the waters and realized she
fornicates with kings. She who was born
with seven heads and had the power and
support of the ten horns as long as
virtue was her husband's pleasure.
You've made yourselves a god of gold and
silver. How are you different from the
idoltors save that they worship one and
you a hundred? Ah Constantine, what
wickedness was born and not from your
conversion from the daer that you
bestowed upon the first rich father?
And while I sang such notes to him,
whether it was his indignation or his
conscience that bit him, he kicked hard
with both his souls.
I do indeed believe it pleased my guide,
he listened always with such satisfied
expression to the sound of those true
words. And then he gathered me in both
his arms, and when he had me fast
against his chest, where he climbed down
before, climbed upward now, nor did he
tire of clasping me until he brought me
to the summit of the arch that crosses
from the fourth to the fifth rampart.
And he and here he gently set his
burdens down gently, because the ridge
was rough and steep, and would have been
a rugged path for goats, for there
another valley lay before me. Okay. So
this is um another one of Donny's um
pirates against the church against
church corruption. Okay. So the crime
the sin that is being punished here is
simony. Okay. What simony is is it's
very common at this time for the church
to sell holy relics to people. And this
was very profitable right? Because think
about it right it's the church. So and a
lot of this a lot of these relics were
fake. But even if they weren't fake, you
shouldn't do that, right? You shouldn't
sell holy relics to the highest bidder.
What is the modern equivalent of simony?
>> Selling offices.
>> Excuse me.
>> Selling offices. Well, they did do that
um back then as well. Okay. So, that's
not the same. But someone else selling
simony. Yes.
>> Maybe taxes.
>> Taxes. Can you explain?
>> Well, um, you pay taxes and in turn the
state promise you that you're safe and
yeah, you have a better life.
>> Okay. So, um, simony is a crime. The
church, even the church condones simony,
right? Because sim is named after Simon
Simon Maggus, who is the first heretic
in the Catholic Church. So, sim is a bad
thing. Everyone knows it's a bad thing.
They kept on doing it. So I'm saying so
in a in our modern world what would the
equivalent be of simony?
>> Selling credentials.
>> Excuse me.
>> Credentials. Selling credentials.
>> Yeah, that's a really good example,
right? Selling diplomas,
right? And do universities engage in
selling diplomas?
>> Oh, legacies.
>> No, no, no, no. It's actually
>> not just that.
How how do universities engage in
selling u credentials? Do you guys know
>> increases the tuition every year?
>> No,
>> they receive donations.
>> Yeah, they receive donations.
>> Yes. Okay. Yeah. Right. Okay. So
donations
um but also like um summer school
continue education like there are lots
of ways in which universities sell uh
their credentials. Okay. Uh any other
examples?
Yes.
Luxury items. So like very expensive
bags or like symbolic items which don't
hold value truly.
>> Right. But so the idea of sim is
corruption, right? You're just abusing
your power and profiting from it. So if
you're a luxury goods uh retailer, I
mean that that's not corruption, right?
So it has to be like a trusted
authority. It could be university, could
it could be government, uh it could be
the church. Okay.
Anyone?
Any other examples?
All right. Uh that's fine. Let's Yes.
Cryptocurrency,
>> excuse me,
>> cryptocurrency.
>> Can you explain?
>> Well, right, a holy relic is itself.
Well, if if C, you know, if the richest
people on the in the world agree that
something is of value and you assign
value to it, you give it an authority,
the rest of society would follow.
Similar to the holy relic, right? I
assign this relic.
I don't know. I don't know if that makes
sense,
>> right? Yeah. So, I I I think your
example is the very best. Okay? Because
uh what's equivalent of the church
today? It's a universities, right? They
have the most authority. They're the
people who they they are the most
trusted institution.
And the fact that, you know, if you just
if you just give them a donation,
they're going to uh fasttrack your
child. Um if you've been following the
news, Stanford, there's a huge case a
lot in Stanford about this, right? Um
there there are lot lots of examples.
Okay. But again, yeah would never do
this. So
right okay let's let's go to uh Infernal
20.
>> Okay. Inferno Kanto 20. I must make
verses of new punishment and offer
matter now for Kanto 20 of this first
canacle of the submerged. I was already
well prepared to stare below into the
depth that was disclosed where tears of
anguish sorrow bathed the ground. In the
valley circle I saw souls advancing mute
and weeping at the pace that in our
world holy processions take. As I
declined my head still more I saw that
each amazingly appeared contorted
between the chin and where the chest
begins. They had their faces twisted
toward their hunches and found it
necessary to walk backward because they
could not see ahead of them.
>> Okay. All right. So this is funnier.
Okay. But like the punishment is that
the people walk around and their heads
are twisted backwards. So they they only
see behind them. They can never see in
front of them. What was their crime in
life? What was their sin? What what what
what do they do?
This is ironic, right? These are people
who going to look behind them.
Fortune teller.
>> Exactly. Right. These are fortune
tellers. These are people who lie to
you, who defraud you and tell you that
you that they could see into the future
and they will give you their future and
um as punishment they can only look
backwards. Um okay,
keep on going.
>> Line 16. Perhaps the force of policy has
so fully distorted some, but that I've
yet to see and I do not believe that
that can be. May God so let you reader
gather fruit from what you read. And now
think for yourself how how I could ever
keep my own face dry when I beheld my
image so nearby and so arrive that tears
down from the eyes bathed the butto
hooks running down the clft. Of course I
wept leaning against a rock along that
rugged ridge so that my guide told me.
Are you as foolish foolish as the rest?
Here pity only lives when it is dead.
For who can be more imp impious than he
who links God's judgment to pacivity.
lift, lift your head and see the one for
whom the earth was opened while the
thieans watched so that they all cried.
And Fieros,
where are you rushing? Have you quit the
fight? Nor did he interrupt his downward
plunge to Minos, who lays hands on every
sinner? See how he's made a chest out of
his shoulders. And since he wanted so to
see ahead, he looks behind and walks a
backward path. And so Terriciss who
changed his mean went from a man he
turned into a woman so totally
transforming all his limbs that then he
had to strike once more upon the two
entwining serpents with his wand before
he had his manly plumes again.
And Arens is the one who backs against
the belly of Teresas. Arens who in
Looney's hails tilled by the Carzi who
lived below had as his home a cave among
white marbles from which he could gaze
at stars and see with unimpeded view.
And she who covers up her breasts, which
you can't see with her disheveled locks,
who keeps all of her hairy parts to the
far side, was Mantto, who had searched
through many lands, then settled in the
place where I was born. On this, I'd
have you hear me now a while.
When Mentos's father took his leaf of
life and Bakasa city found itself
enslaved, she wandered through the world
for many years. High up in lovely Italy
beneath the elves that shut in Germany
above Terolo lies a lake known as
Bonakco. A thousand springs and more I
think must flow out of the waters of
that lake to bathe Panino Gardo Valkam
Monica. And in its middle is a place
where three the bishops of Verona
breasto
may bless if they should chance to come
that way. Presciera strong and handsome
fortress built to face the breastians
and the burgamas stands when the
circling shore is at its lowest. There
all the waters that cannot be held
within the bosom of binoco to form a
river running through green meadows. No
sooner has that stream begun to flow
than it is called the Mincchio, not
Bakaco, until Gvernolo, where it joins
the Poe. It's not flowed far before it
finds flat land, and there it stretches
out to form a fen that in the summer can
at times be fed. And when she passed
that way, the savage virgin saw land
along the middle of the swamp until
stripped of its inhabitants.
And there to flee all human intercourse
she halted with her slaves to ply her
arts and there she lived there left her
empty body. And after with the people of
those parts collected at that place
because the marsh surrounding it on all
sides made it strong. They built a city
over her dead bones. And after her who
first had picked that spot they called
it Manua. They cast no lots. There once
were far more people in its walls before
the foolishness of Kasalodi was tricked
by the deceit of Pinamonte.
Therefore, I charge you, if you ever
hear a different tale of my town's
origin, do not let any falsehood gull
the truth.
And I, oh master, that which you have
spoken convinces me, and so compels my
trust that others words would only be
spent coals. But tell me if among the
passing souls you see some spirits
worthy of our notice because my mind is
spent on that alone. Then he to me that
shade who spreads his beard down from
his cheeks across his sworthy shoulders
when grease had been so emptied of its
males that hardly any cradle held the
sun. He was an augur and at all he and
Calus at the time to cut the cables. His
name's Uripololis. A certain passage of
my high tragedy has sung it so you know
that well enough who know the whole. The
other there his flanks extremely spare
was Michael Scott a man who certainly
knew how the game of magic fraud was
played. See there Guido Bonati see
Estente who now would wish he had
attended to his court and leather but
repense too late.
See those sad women who had left their
needle, shuttle and spindle to become
divorc.
They cast their spells with herbs and
effiges, but let us go. Cain with his
thorns already is at the border of both
hemispheres and there below Sevilla
torches touches the sea. Last night the
moon was at its full. You should be a
well well aware of this. For there were
times when it did you no harm in the
deep wood. These were his words to me.
Meanwhile, we journeyed.
>> Okay, so this is about the fortune
tellers. Okay, they are condemned to
always walk with their uh head turned
backwards. So they can they can never
see in front of them. They going see
behind them. And
Dante spends a lot of time talking about
all these uh fortune tellers and sages
of integrity. Okay, Teresus is a really
famous
um fortune tell fortune teller the most
famous oracle in Greek mythology. Uh the
man who told or um uh Edypus that uh he
in fact did kill his father and slept
with his mother. Okay, Terissus.
Why is Donnie spending so much time
on the fortune tellers? What is his what
is his problem with fortune tellers or
oracles?
I mean, isn't he an oracle? Sorry. Go
ahead.
>> Yeah. I think that's why the Bible
speaks against uh this kind of fortune
telling is one of the biggest sins. It's
because you denied yourself of free will
because once you have been given, oh,
tomorrow you will die or whatever and
you're like, oh, you're going to
self-fulfill that prophecy. So like
whatever the fortune teller tells you
kind of sets your path and you don't
have the free will to live out your life
anymore.
>> Okay, that's one possibility, right? Um
just to deny you free will,
right? Because if if you remember the
story of um Edypus Rex, right? He was
told uh his father was told uh your your
son will kill you and marry your wife.
He became so afraid that he abandoned
his son or had his he tried to have his
son killed which then set in motion this
prophecy. Okay. And then when um uh
Edypus was adopted by another royal
family in his uh teenage years, he he
heard this prophecy and he ran away from
his father which then completed the
prophecy because on the in on the on his
way to uh thieves, he would get in
conflict with with his father with the
king, his father, and kill him and then
he'd go and solve the riddle of the spin
and then which would allow him to marry
his mother. Okay. and become king of
thieves. So this um so the idea of free
will, right? You can choose whatever you
want. It's hampered by these prophecies
because then you're just a great a pawn
in the game of the gods, right?
Okay. Like this prophecy is the idea
like the gods want things a certain way
and that's why they give you this
prophecy in order to manipulate you into
behaving the way that they want. Okay.
Yes. Any other explanations for why he
really Donn really really doesn't like
these fortune tellers? He doesn't really
like like the idea of fortune telling.
>> Uh yes,
>> if you're a big fortune teller, if you
become a famous fortune teller, the net
effect is you reducing the total amount
of imagination that that you know your
your population or your c the people
that you preach to have. So really is
restricting the level of creativity,
imagination that God ultimately wants to
grow, not shrink.
>> Sure. Yes. Exactly. And also a lot of
these fortune tellers are doing for
profit, right? They they often do it to
make money. Yes.
>> Yeah. Because fortune tellers just keep
telling you that everything is fake.
It's fixed. You can't change. So it
means that there's no free will and uh
you can just choose what you want and
you just listen. So some people may be
against this and some people agree with
that but whatever you agree or disagree
uh the fraging just try to uh you know
disturb you and change you change your
your your original will.
>> Okay. Yes. Uh anyone else
have you guys did do you remember um the
book of um Exodus when Moses gets in a
fight with the uh with the um priests of
the Pharaoh?
And they have they had like this magic
contest. C can you can you talk about
that Carol or
>> is it when they were leaving and so they
had to against the 10 gods of the
Pharaoh. Is that what it is before they
leave?
>> Uh yes.
>> Of the gods. Yes.
>> Oh okay. So basically Moses was like
yeah Israelites have to go out of Egypt.
And the king of Egypt was like no we
want to enslave you free labor. So then
they put up the contest between the
gods. So there were the 10 plagues. So
each plague was against each god of the
the Egyptians.
>> Yes. Okay. So there there's actually
quite a few of these contests in the
Bible. Okay. The the prophet to pro
prove himself he must go to war with
other fortune tellers with other
divinators to prove that I am truly the
messenger from heaven. Okay. And to do
that I'm going to show that every one of
you is fake and false. Does that make
sense? So Dante I mean there there are
many motivations but one m major
motivation is that Dante is trying to
prove that he is the ultimate prophet by
showing that every other fortune teller
is just a fraud. Okay. Does that make
sense? Okay. So then let me ask yes.
>> There's a part in the passage where
Dante actually has a for me he has a
kind of an unusual reaction. He feels
kind of sad looking at the the the
creatures with the your head backwards.
Right.
>> Yes. But that's but that's Dante's
reaction to everyone, right? He's like,
I pity this.
>> Okay.
>> And and it goes back to the idea of
Aristotle like why is important to watch
theater? Like why is it important to go
to theater and why is theater Yes.
>> You see the tragedy of yourself in them.
>> Yes. Exactly right. This is part of
something called the ctharsis process.
He is in hell to purge himself of his
fear and his pride and his anger. And
the way you do that is by pitying other
people. And this this is what creates
the ctharsis and allows you to be a new
person.
>> I mean back to the luck media, right?
Like initially Dante called this luck
media. It was only afterwards that it
was proven to be divine. Right.
>> Right.
>> So I'm wondering if he's kind of worried
too like if if this is I'm only doing
like you know am I if I'm not fully
channeling channeling the divine here
will will I end up in the same situation
here?
>> Sure. Sure. But but he's pretty
confident that that he is the true
prophet. Okay. Otherwise, he would not
be writing uh the Divine Comedy. Um
what proves that he is the true prophet
to Dante?
If you're a fortune teller and you
predict some predict something, right,
then that shows you are the true
prophet. But Donnie doesn't do that. So,
how does Stony prove he's the true
prophet?
And he he's able to convince a lot of
people he's a true prophet. How
>> before the plague came.
>> Well, yeah. Well, he died before the
plague, right?
The beauty of his poetry, right? Does
that make sense? It's so beautiful that
you're moved to tears and you are
convinced that he must be the prophet,
right? because otherwise how else could
he have conjured up such beautiful
poetry. Okay. Um let me ask you this
question uh and and we'll end because we
we we've been going a long time. Um and
we'll sort of finish Divine Comedy uh
over the next two days. If so, in our
present day, what kind of people will be
condemned to hell with their heads
um turned backwards? And like I don't
know the answer, but I'm just curious as
to what who who you might think would be
condemned to hell with this sort of
punishment.
And again, I don't know the answer. I'm
just asking you guys, well, who you
think might deserve such a punishment?
We don't have fortune tellers today,
right? But who what kind of people?
>> There are a lot of fortune tellers
today. Actually, fortune telling is
quite invogue now
>> in Asia and in China. Yeah.
>> Yes. I think fake news so like media
newspaper like in a way to move public
opinion so that it fulfills the prophecy
that the media wants or
yes
>> people with an agenda fake I guess you
can call it fake news um people within
it the the larger agenda trying to make
something happen and then they using all
these channels for communication they're
restricting imagination right going back
to the concept of restricting people's
imagination trying to capture them into
one reality that you want to have.
>> No, no, no. I happen to agree. I think
uh very influential journalists today
that clearly have an agenda. Um they are
the modern day modern day equivalent of
fortune tellers, right? Because the way
that you would influence a king is you
would bribe a fortune teller to tell him
what he wants to hear and that would
cause him to do what what you wanted.
And and that's what um journalists,
podcasters, YouTube celebrities, but not
me of course um
That's what they do, right? Um, so yes,
>> it goes back to imagination. If if your
act of broadcast, whatever that content
that you put out, if if that is, is it a
net positive or a net negative on on on
on imagination, on people's ability to
think for themselves. Right.
>> Right. And how and how would you
differentiate between good and bad?
>> No, no. [snorts] People's ability to
think for themselves. Not necessarily
good or bad. Right. Um,
right. If if I I I I I inject something
with emotion and I try to push it push
it push it force feed it to to to the
larger population that's going to be
similar to fortune teller. Right.
>> Yes.
>> I think people are um people that are
bad are those who trying to con trying
to convince you into believing something
without letting you even question it or
um just letting just just without
letting you know that you're being
influenced by them. um and your
imagination is influenced or even
narrowed down by them into believing
something fixed that they want you to
believe. But um like you said uh that's
why I think you are not this kind of
person cuz you never um you never like
uh don't let us to to to um imagine for
ourselves and and um propose our own um
arguments against or not against you.
>> Okay. Thank you for that. Any more
comments? Yeah, because I think
Hollywood always make a lot of films and
all of the blockbusters just try to keep
telling you some kind of the you know uh
to predict the future for example like
Terminator or some kind of films like
the Avatar or you know maybe Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Again that that that gives you a
possible um explanation, right? Not the
not that they're they're like trying to
convince you this is what going to
happen. They they give you a
possibility. So, do you think that's
also a fortune teller in a way that it
>> Okay. All right. So, so I don't spend
too much time on on this on this idea
and also I'll I'll get in trouble
because you guys will name names and
then he'll interview me and he'll he'll
like shout at me for an hour. Okay. But
like um we have looked at a list of
society decline. Okay. Are there any
major things that are missing from this
list that that that you want to point
out? So for example the idea of a
meritocracy which is an intense
competition for few and fewer uh uh
resources. You have access and
arrogance, pride, fraud. You have the
lack of social mobility, lack of
openness, uh uh homosexuality, incest
among the elite because they want to
exclude everyone else, right? Uh too
much self-love, too much
self-indulgence, too much individuality,
too much immigration. Yes. I feel like
extreme wealth inequality.
>> Yes, exactly. Great. Extreme wealth in
quality. Yes.
>> Self-indulgence.
>> Self-indulgence. Yes.
>> Um not being able to express um one's
own opinions.
>> Yes. Censorship.
>> Exactly. Exactly. That that's very
important. Yes. I I I want to write this
down. Okay. Um
>> sorry.
I mean, the fact that when we talked
about homosexuality,
um, like, you know, I'm nervous about
being cancelled on YouTube, right? I'm
being stoned to death at Yale. Yes. Yes.
>> Um, increased.
>> Yes. Um I think censorship is a problem
but um like in some well you can you can
actually
say whatever you want or like think
whatever you want but the fact that you
cannot change
>> no you can't no you cannot no you cannot
if if you if this were were at Yale and
I said you know homosexuality could be
bad I'd be in a lot of trouble
>> with I would get fired I'm not I'm I'm
not joking here okay you cannot say
whatever you want you just
Yes.
>> To decrease trust in social institutions
including the media, the government.
>> Yes. That's really important in the
breakdown of authority. Yes. Exactly.
The breakdown of authority.
This is really important.
>> The reality is that today there are no
institutions that can be trusted
anymore. Right. Um before in the United
States you had Congress, you had
science, you had the military, you had
universities. Now none of these
institutions are trusted. Uh yes
>> to that point also um increased
bureaucracy or power like bureaucrats
having a lot of power.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Maybe postmodernism.
So like the annalation of all the
trusted authorities before like the
cancel culture movement building up. We
>> call this postruuth.
>> Yeah. Postruth era.
>> Post truth.
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
You can't even talk about what's true or
not. Uh yes.
>> Uh I would say directed education. So
giving one definition of what it means
to be successful.
>> Exactly. Yes. Um a narrow definition of
success. Yes. Uh yes.
>> Degradation in the
aesthetic standards.
>> Okay. Great. So I'm convinced we are
totally screwed. Okay. All right. So
that's it for today. I'll save on
tomorrow.